<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The just mans defence, or, The royal conquest being the declaration of the judgement of James Arminius, Doctor of Divinity in the University of Leyden, concerning the principall points of religion, before the States of Holland and VVestfriezland / translated for the vindication of truth, by Tobias Conyers, sometimes of Peter-house in Cambridge.</title>
            <title>Declaratio sententiae de predestinatione. English</title>
            <author>Arminius, Jacobus, 1560-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3700A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875715</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152178</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152178)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2281:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The just mans defence, or, The royal conquest being the declaration of the judgement of James Arminius, Doctor of Divinity in the University of Leyden, concerning the principall points of religion, before the States of Holland and VVestfriezland / translated for the vindication of truth, by Tobias Conyers, sometimes of Peter-house in Cambridge.</title>
                  <title>Declaratio sententiae de predestinatione. English</title>
                  <author>Arminius, Jacobus, 1560-1609.</author>
                  <author>Conyers, Tobias, 1628-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 156, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by Henry Eversden ...</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Declaratio sententiae de predestinatione.</note>
                  <note>Pages 18, 32, 79 incorrectly numbered 81, 22, 7, respectively.</note>
                  <note>Headpiece; initial. Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Predestination.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:2"/>
            <p>The Juſt Mans Defence, <hi>OR, The Royal Conqueſt:</hi> BEING The Declaration of the Judgement of <hi>James Arminius,</hi> Doctor and Profeſſor of Divinity in the Univerſity of <hi>Leyden;</hi> Concerning THE PRINCIPALL POINTS of <hi>Religion,</hi> before the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>VVestfriezland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated for the Vindication of Truth, by</hi> Tobias Conyers, <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of</hi> Peter-houſe <hi>in</hi> Cambridge.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Magna est veritas &amp; praevalebit.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author; and are to be ſold by <hi>Henry Everſden,</hi> at the <hi>Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:3"/>
            <head>TO HIS HIGHNESS, <hi>Oliver,</hi> Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Great Britain and Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Great Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Preſume the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of theſe papers without any Apologie to your Lordſhip, having been already preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to States and Princes; not that your Highneſs (in whom ſo many princely ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are conſtellated) ſtood in need of a tranſlation, but
<pb facs="tcp:152178:4"/> that an obvious Dialect might ſuperſede the pains of an Original Traverſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto your Lordſhip all poſſible time to ſatisfie the importunity of thoſe affairs which do publickly ſolicite you for a diſpatch of them. Had not the concernments of truth been of greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to me then any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal conſideration (though I am not ſtupidly inſenſible) I ſhould have been loth my Lord—But in as much as the name of <hi>Arminians</hi> is violently obtruded upon us, who beleeve that Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all, and taſted death for every man according to the Scriptures, whereby our perſons are indevoured to be rendered odious, and the bleſſed word of the kingdom
<pb facs="tcp:152178:4"/> in our mouths ſcandalous and offenſive, I judged it reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to offer the authors judgment to Engliſh view; not that <hi>I</hi> deſire the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſhould be lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the interpretation of mine (being never yet drawn by any inquiſitory examini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to a full approbation or diſlike of it) but that I might put an opportunity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of indifferent men, of reſolving themſelves that <hi>Arminius</hi> was no ſuch monſter in religion as ſome men have attempted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent him, and that his name ſtands undeſervedly blotted in the <hi>Eccleſiastick Rolls</hi> of continual obloquie. It was a worthy eſſay of Your Highneſs upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at Whitehall; That it was
<pb facs="tcp:152178:5"/> not ſo much what a man held, but how he held it; (A religous calenture hath alwaies been a dangerous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie in the Eye of State-Phyſitians) <hi>I</hi> am confident the Doctor in this draught of himſelf will abundantly pleaſe you, in whom Learning and Ingenuity, Piety and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration contend together for the maſtery, and this by the happy ducture of chriſtian Principles; which if the like tenderneſs, candour and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty had been uſed by the Reformed Churches in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> they had not given that cauſe by their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and diſobedience to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and other perſons of great and leſſer quality to complain of them, and indevour the extirpatati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:152178:5"/> of their religion. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thoſe ſad Maſſacres in <hi>France;</hi> that lately in <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> ſo fatal to the <hi>Hugonets</hi> barracado'd from the ſtroke of juſtice with their own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines.</p>
            <p>It would not become me to unravell this bottom, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping by the timely interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Your Lordſhips wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and goodneſs, with the care and prudence of thoſe noble Patriots about you, we may not have ground (in things of leſs alloy) to expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate in our own Country: Its well known (my Lord) what countenance the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures carry with the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of general atonement, and how much it looks like the doctrine of the Church of England (ſo we call it)
<pb facs="tcp:152178:6"/> and that the major part of the Biſhops and Doctors during the Epiſcopal Hierarchy, were deeply babtized there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into, and the late King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: yet did they never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance piety and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in men of the contrary judgment, either in Country or Univerſity, by rendering them uncapable of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either Civil or Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astick, or draw them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant their opinions before their inſtitution and inducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into any place; witneſs the credit and promotion of <hi>Sibbs, Preston, Pridjeux, Holds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, Bromrig, Love, Hall,</hi> &amp;c. Nay great <hi>Strafford</hi> preſident of the Court in the North, did in the hearing of ſome perſons, who are ſtill living teſtimonies thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:152178:6"/> publickly rebuke ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Arminian party ſo called (though he himſelf a great promoter of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt) for bearing themſelves high upon court favour, and told them, it was the will of his maſter and the Doctors of the Church, that all modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be uſed herein. The Scoene is altered; theſe pluck't off the ſtage, and your Lordſhip taken up. I ſhould be highly injurious to thoſe many ſacred vows and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations your Highneſs hath ſo often made for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty, ſhould I enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a thought you would act your part with leſs ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and indulgency than any of thoſe that have had their fatal Exit. My Lord, You have been a man of
<pb facs="tcp:152178:7"/> War, Liberty was that <hi>Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> in your <hi>Enſign</hi> which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the Soldiers of Chriſt to fight and pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you, &amp; for which I make no queſtion victory came ſo often and lighed upon your banner: <hi>I</hi> beſeech you by the mercies of God, and by what ever is dear or near unto you, that you would not expoſe us by your authority to the wills of thoſe who are ſo ſtraitned in their principles, as their affections, in brotherly tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration are ſhut up againſt us likewiſe; but that all your Acts of Grace, like the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Heaven iſſuing out from your great Maſter, may impartially look to the good of all. I cannot (with the zeal of <hi>Arminius</hi>) petition your Highneſs for a Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb facs="tcp:152178:7"/> Synod, and to eſtabliſh Eccleſiaſtick Sanctions by ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill authority, left in have the ſame event (or ſomwhat<note place="margin">An. 1618, &amp; 1619.</note> worſe) with the <hi>Dort-Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> but (ſalving the honor and conſciences of thoſe Gentlemen, the commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for Approbation of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters) I muſt needs think the nature of Orthodox and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodox would be better prov'd by a ſubſcription to a known Confeſſion of Faith drawn up in Scripture terms &amp; phraſes, according to w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Preachers of the Goſpel might &amp; ought to frame and level their judgments and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines; then by the ſudden and extempore reſolves to a few unpredimeditated Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions (till the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) lockt up in the breaſts of ſome particular men.
<pb facs="tcp:152178:8"/> And this I am bold to offer to your Lordſhip, not as to one of <hi>Machiavells Princes,</hi> who will not follow Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion too cloſe at the heels; or to a Roman <hi>Gallio, who careth for none of theſe things;</hi> but as to a <hi>good Joſiah,</hi> whoſe heart <hi>melted at the hearing of the Law,</hi> and covenanted with his God, to take away all the abominations out of all the Countreys that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained<note place="margin">2 Chron. 34 35.</note> to the Children of Iſrael. That no <hi>Pharaoh Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> may come up againſt you, and the people of this Land; but that peace and proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may attend You, and your Name be as apretious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment poured out upon the inhabitants of Zion, is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Highneſs's moſt humble Servant, Tobias Conyers.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>June 5. 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:8"/>
            <head>To the CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ts the chief intent of the Author (as far as I can judge) next to the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Truth, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to ſet thy judgment right in the great points of Predeſtination and Providence, and to ſhow the happy compliance 'twixt the free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merited grace of God and Mans Will, not ſacrilegiouſly addmitting the latter as a copartner with the former in the work of converſion; but with much reſpect ſubordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the one to the other, reſerving unto each their peculiar vertues and operations, making the new creation ſo to animate the old, as to reſtore weakned powers and debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated faculties to much of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſtrength &amp; vigor, and fit them for action. Surely had I thought
<pb facs="tcp:152178:9"/> the Doctor had been an enemie to grace (as too many of the great Clerks of the world are) I ſhould have wiſhed his Judgment had for ever ſlept in darkneſs and never been awaked by me or any other to ſee the Engliſh light! But by that lively portraiture which he hath drawn of himſelf, I am apt to think his mind was well beautified with many fair</hi> Ideas <hi>of Truth, and his underſtanding enlightened with a raie from that divine ſight which</hi> ſighteth every one that cometh<note place="margin">John 1. 9.</note> into the world; <hi>I cannot attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the growth and encreaſe of the Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alapſarian &amp; Sublapſarian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in ſome of the reformd Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to any thing ſo much as the untutord zeal of ſome men (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe eminent in their generation) in the beginning of reformation; who having fallen out with the church of Rome, and that upon the account of their ſtrange innovations, and ungodly errours, their Maſs, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, works, merit, indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
<pb facs="tcp:152178:9"/> pardons, &amp;c. they tore away indeed much of this Superſtition, and teſtified to the world their diſlike of all ſuch erroneous Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents &amp; curſed practiſes: But when like wiſe Chirurgians they ſhould have known when the cure had been nigh finiſhed, they ſtill continued launcing the ſore deeper and deeper till they had let out ſome of the very vitals of Religion, and maimd the doctrine of Chriſtianity in ſome of the principal members thereof. What was Orthodox at</hi> Rome <hi>muſt needs be Heterodox at</hi> Geneva, <hi>for fear (as I imagine) least the Orifice ſhould cloſe, and the Body Eccleſiaſtick return to its former temper</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">A good end is not to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by ſiniſter &amp; indirect means.</note> 
               <hi>How doth</hi> Calvin <hi>beat his head thorough the whole body of his</hi> Inſtitutions <hi>(the more to alienate, as I conceive, the minds of men from the Romiſh Religion) to draw up the Proteſtant Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the greatest contrariety ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to thoſe of</hi> Rome, <hi>fearing leaſt he ſhould never get far enough
<pb facs="tcp:152178:10"/> both in doctrine and diſcipline from them: Think not Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I favour the</hi> Romiſh Church <hi>herein, or intend to throw dirt in the face of the</hi> Reform'd, <hi>(this were to ſlander my mother, and reproach the womb that bare me) I only labour thy ſatisfaction, and by a modeſt diſquiſition, to light thee in to the riſe and grounds of this controverſie. Neither am I ingaged in my judgment againſt all or half of the Proteſtant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the major part are of the ſame mind in the doctrine of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the author will ſatisfie thee in the enſueing diſcourſe. I know no rigid Predeſtinarians, but thoſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Sabauda <hi>and</hi> Geneva, <hi>the Preſbiterate</hi> Scots, <hi>who (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient-league and freindſhip to comply with the French) have fetch't much of their Religion thence, and thoſe at home upon whoſe Spirits the doctrine of the</hi> Kirk <hi>hath been too much aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. Yet what great reſpect I
<pb facs="tcp:152178:10"/> have born to the opinion of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and learned brethren diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting herein, even to the ſhaking of my own faith, being more ready to accuſe my ſelf of pride, ignorance, and ſingularity (the uſual parents of errour) then them of unſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I have abundantly teſtified, privately and publickly; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> Mr. Richard Copeman <hi>a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gentleman and a Justice of Peace for the County of</hi> Norffolk, <hi>&amp; many others, though of a different opinion, will be my witneſs: The more I came to ſearch into the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and being of that great</hi> Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah <hi>reveald in the word of life, the more I found it unworthy of the enter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tainment of a Chriſtians heart, that no way could be found out by infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite wiſdome to glorifie the divine Attributes, but by the preciſe ordination of almoſt infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his children to eternal and remedileſs torments, without the leaſt intuition or reſpect to their ſin and diſobedience: I ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb facs="tcp:152178:11"/> that I were a creature (which the egritudes and infirmities of ſoul and body do dayly admoniſh me of) were I unwilling to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that great prerogative of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Gods Soveraignty over me, yet ſhould I be a paraſite in religion in attributing any thing to divine power, but what his Juſtice, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Goodneſs permits me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 13. 7. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Will a man tell a lye for God—I ſolemnly profeſs, I know not with what hope of advantage I ſhould propound Christ as an object of faith in a generall exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the people, if he dyed not for them; certainly the ſecret will of God is the ſame with his reveald, he is unskild in the art of diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; his words alwaies agree with his mind; let God be true and every man a lyar. I cannot be of the judgment of</hi> Piſcator, <hi>who</hi>
               <note place="margin">Piſc. reſp. ad vors. Part 1. pag. 120.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith reprobate perſons are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ordained to this twofold evil, to undergo everlaſting puniſhment, and neceſſarily ſin, and therefore to
<pb facs="tcp:152178:11"/> ſin that they might be juſtly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch. lib. 5. de nat. Dei, cap. 2. de Predeſt.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Zanchy <hi>tells us that reprobates are held ſo faſt under Gods Almighty decree, that they cannot but ſin and periſh. Its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Gods love to Mankind.</note> 
               <hi>of</hi> Tiberius, <hi>upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the fall of</hi> Elius Sejanus <hi>raiſed for the ruin of the houſe of</hi> Germanicus, <hi>being reſolved to leave no ſtemme to grow out af that unhappy root, purpoſd to put the young and tender daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of</hi> Sejanus <hi>to death, the Roman laws forbiding to ſtrangle a Virgin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peter Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Ep.</note> 
               <hi>he cauſ'd her to be defloured by the executioner, at the foot of the</hi> Gemonian <hi>ſtaires, and then ſtrangled: Pardon O good God the teachers of thy Church, who have publiſhed thy unalterable reſolves in thy eternal decree of putting to everlaſting death infinite numbers of virgin and undefloured ſouls (the righteous laws of heaven not permitting it) thy determinations likewiſe that ſin and Satan ſhould firſt vitiate and conſtuprate them: If this were once generally received
<pb facs="tcp:152178:12"/> that men ſin neceſſarily and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably, and all that they do in purſueance of the divine decree, what would this introduce but Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iciſm and Manichiſme? would it not be an inlet to all looſneſſe and licentiouſneſſe, an inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all barbariſm and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in fine this undergovern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the world ſuffer a diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? But O my deare Brother! labour to eſchew evill, and do good, and be confident his grace will be ſufficient for thee. Say not in thy heart I am ſhut out from the love of God, I am as a dry tree: draw neere to this communicative and diffuſive love of God, that thy ſoule may be drenched therewith: I am very well aſſured by the bleſſed word of truth, there ſtands no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Reprobation, like the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubim in the garden of Eden with a flaming ſword in it's hand, to keep the way from the greater part of men to the tree of life: God is not contributory by any voluntary
<pb facs="tcp:152178:12"/> purpoſe or act to the perdition of any of his Creatures; yet is he ſo great a lover if righteouſneſſe and juſtice that he will puniſh ſin unrepented of where ever he finds it. Above all things purſue peace with all men if't be poſſible, and holineſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no man ſhall ſee the Lord, take not up any thing cantain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe papers for contention, ſtrife, and debate; O flee vaine janglings, which defile the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, corrupt the heart, and tend not to edification! The church of God is too too much made an Amphytheater; Religion a meere digladiation; the ſeverall opinions the combatants, the weapon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and not Spirituall, and the prize (I fear) Self-glory, and ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advancement. If thou knoweſt theſe things, happy art thou if thou</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 13. 17</note> 
               <hi>doeſt them, let thy knowledge looke to practice, as the fruit, and thy practice to knowledg, as the guide; and be aſſured, they will both lead to hapineſſe, as the end: But, not
<pb facs="tcp:152178:13"/> to ſwell this Epiſtle beyond its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, let me tell thee, thou muſt vouchfafe this peece a diligent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſall, if thou wouldeſt reap any profit by it; expect not Rhetoricall flouriſhes to court thee with entic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words of vanity into the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours judgment, or the ſoft ſtrains of Eloquence to touch thee with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; this the mind of the Authour, the nature of the thing, and the tranſlation it ſelf forbids thee.</hi> Try all things (<hi>by the teſt of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi>) hold faſt that which is good,<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Never the leſſe, whereto we have already attained,</hi> let us walke by the ſame rule, let us minde the ſame things, and if in any thing thou he otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this unto thee:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>June 5. 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152178:13"/>
            <head>TO THE Noble and Potent STATES OF <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>VVeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friezland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Supreme Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt M. <hi>Gomar</hi> and my ſelf at the <hi>Hague</hi> by the command of your Highneſſes, before the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152178:14"/> Lords Counſellors of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court, four Miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent, and relation made thereof to your Highneſſes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating the weight and moment of the Controverſie betwixt us, it afterward was thought requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite by your noble Highneſſes, to call both of us together, with the four Miniſters, before you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your honourable Aſſembly, to ſignifie to us all this way what you ſhould judge moſt expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for that time; So it fell out, Mr. <hi>Gomar</hi> confirm'd the debate a foot betwixt us, to be of that grand importance, that he durſt not joyn iſſue with ſuch an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as this of mine, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God; and more then that, if it were not preſently ſtopt, 'twould ſet the Provinces, Churches, Cities, and Citizens together by the ears, and every mans hand againſt his brother. To all which I anſwered nothing at that time, ſave that I knew not my ſelf guilty of any ſuch cruel
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152178:14"/> opinion in Religion, being confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent I ſhould never adminiſter any juſt cauſe or ground for Schiſm or diſſention to build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either in Church or State; in teſtimony whereof I was ready openly in all truth and ſincerity to declare my mind in the whole matter of Religion, when ever I ſhould be commanded thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to before this Aſſembly, and that before I removed from the place where I then ſtood.</p>
            <p>Upon which motion, it was judged convenient by your Highneſſes that I ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before you now to make good the proffer in theſe Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and therefore it is that I now appear in this place faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to diſcharge it. But in as much as a ſiniſter report of mee hath for ſo long a time ſpread it ſelf not only at home, but abroad in forrain parts, and no little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill hath enſued thereupon, as if I had hitherto altogether refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (being often required there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152178:15"/> to declare my judgement in the buſineſs of Religion; Wherefore I make it my humble requeſt that you'l pleaſe to give me leave ingenuouſly to open my ſelf in this matter before I proceed to other things.</p>
            <p>In the yeer 1605. June 30. There came to me at <hi>Leyden</hi> three Deputies of the Synod of South-Holland, <hi>viz. Francis Lansberge, Libert Fraxim,</hi> and <hi>Daniel Volege</hi> of happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Miniſters of their reſpective Churches at Roterdam, the Hague and Delph, being preſent with them two Miniſters of the Synod of North-Holland, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Iohn Bogard</hi> of the Church at Harleme, and <hi>Iames Roland</hi> of the Church at Amſterdam, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me in their Claſſical Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of ſome Students in the Univerſity of Leyden, in order to their entrance into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, they received ſome new and unuſual anſwers to the queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152178:15"/> propounded, contrary to the received Doctrine in the Churches, which they confirmed as having been diſciplined into them by me; which things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, they deſired a friendly conference with me to know the bottom of this matter, whereby for the future they might better conſult the affairs of the Church. To which I anſwered I could no way approve this manner of proceſs, which would neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ever and anon multiply confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence upon conference, even as oft as any Student ſhould give any new anſwer, pretending to have learn'd the ſame of me; therefore 'twas better in my judgment, when any Schollar ſhould frame any new Reſponſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his Examinations, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the ſame from me, which ſhould bee judged by the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren contrary to the Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Catechiſm of the <hi>Belgick Churches,</hi> they would ſend for us both together, being ready
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152178:16"/> upon this account at my owne charge to come whereever it ſhould pleaſe the Brethren to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point; and this courſe being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken once and again, the calumny or truth would plainly bee evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>And further to Mr. <hi>Lansberge,</hi> urging the conference in the name of the reſt, anſwer was made, that as yet I ſaw not how I could admit of any ſuch thing with them, appearing as Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from the Synod to whom they ſtood bound to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all things done by them, unleſs my Superiours were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe privy, and conſenting, and alſo commanding me hereunto; beſides it's being joyned with no ſmall hazard, if ſo be I ſhould wholly caſt my ſelfe upon their faithfulneſs in their own relation of the event of our conference to the Synod. And further, that they had no cauſe why they ſhould require any ſuch thing of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152178:16"/> me, not conſcious to my ſelf of delivering any Doctrine either at <hi>Leyden</hi> or <hi>Amsterdam</hi> contrary to the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God, Confeſſion,</hi> or <hi>Catechiſm</hi> of the <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> That hitherto not any ſuch thing was ever objected to me, being confident it would not eaſily be effected, if the Objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſhould be obliged to make good his Objections by proof; and in default thereof, to bear the blame himſelf. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding if they would wave the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Deputation,</hi> and proceed in their own name to a confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with me, I was ready at that inſtant to imbrace it; provided that in every point to be deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they would explaine their judgment, and I mine, each of us alledging our proofs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating one anothers judgments and reaſons; if by this means we could ſatisfie one another, well and good; if not, no further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſhould be made of it, but the whole matter deferred till a <hi>National Synod.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152178:17"/>
            <p>This being refuſed, we had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted aſunder; had I not deſired them, that in like manner they would move a Conference to Mr. <hi>Gomar,</hi> &amp; <hi>Trelcatius</hi> of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memory, not judging my ſelf to have given greater cauſe to them of ſuch a motion as this, then either of them had done. The grounds of this my requeſt I then added, which were too long now to repeat: To which they anſwered they would do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and that before their departure from <hi>Leyden;</hi> and ſo they did, as they themſelves told me.</p>
            <p>And this was the firſt requeſt of this nature that ever was made to me, which occaſion'd much Diſcourſe; ſome giving a Narrative thereof imperfectly, and not as the whole matter was carried, ſmothering in ſilence the motion made by me, and the grounds thereof. Not many dayes after, about the 28. of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in the ſame yeere 1605. the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152178:17"/> like was required by me in the Name of the Synodry of the Church of <hi>Leyden,</hi> yet with this <hi>Proviſo,</hi> That if I approved of it, others likewiſe ſhould be moved unto the ſame; if not, they would not proceed any further in this caſe: But when I had ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified my diſlike (with the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereof) herein to the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough-Maſter <hi>Brouchovius,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Merula,</hi> of godly memory, the Elders and Deputies ſent to me in the Name of the ſaid Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod they were ſo well ſatisfied therewith, that nothing was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther attempted by them in this buſineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>November</hi> the 9th. in the ſame yeer, <hi>Francis Lansberge, Festus Hommius,</hi> and their Aſſociates, Deputies of the Synod of <hi>South-Holland,</hi> exhibited nine queſtions to the Lords Viſitors of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of of <hi>Leyden,</hi> with a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition annexed, that they would pleaſe to command the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Divinity to anſwer to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152178:18"/> ſame. The Lords Viſitors retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Arminius</hi> was now Profeſſor of Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi>
               </note> that they could not approve the Propoſal of any ſuch queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Profeſſors of Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; if they ſuppoſed any thing to be taught in the Univerſity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Truth, it was to be refer'd to the National Synod; (which was hoped to be had very ſhortly) in which they might more fully come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and debate of it. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this Reply, the Deputies of the Synod further urged, that with their good leave they themſelves would propound them to the Profeſſors <hi>S. T.</hi> to know what every of them would voluntarily and freely anſwer thereunto; but neither could this likewiſe be obtained by them. All this being done without my knowledge, being ignorant why theſe Deputies came to the City, although not long after I came to know it.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the whole yeer paſſed over, and I was not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152178:18"/> called upon again touching this matter, except <hi>Anno</hi> 1607. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before the Synod of <hi>South-Holland</hi> was held at <hi>Delphe,</hi> there came to me <hi>Iohn Barnard</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Delphe, Feſtus Hommius</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> and <hi>Dibbetius</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Dort,</hi> to know of me what I had done in the refutation of the Anabaptiſts, of which giving them an account, it afforded matter of much diſcourſe to us; being about to take their leave, they moved if I had done any thing in the buſineſs of Religion; that I would not think much to communicate the ſame to them, and they to the Synod, to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Brethren herein; which I could not conſent unto, in that it could not be with that fruit, fitneſs, and advantage any where as in the National Synod, which wee hoped upon the firſt opportunity, to be celebrated according to the purpoſe of the noble and potent <hi>Lords</hi> the <hi>States;</hi> and there I would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152178:19"/> openly to maniſeſt my thoughts, not being reſerved in any thing of which they might complain. To which I added, if I ſhould open my ſelf in any thing to them, I could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the relation of it to their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, every one in things of this nature being his own beſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter; and ſo we took our leaves one of another.</p>
            <p>Beſides all theſe, I was private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſired by ſome Miniſters, that I would vouchſafe to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate my Meditations to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Brethren in the Synod. By others I was moved to declare my thoughts to them, which in the fear of God, they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider amongſt themſelves, giving their Faith not to divulge them. To the firſt of theſe I anſwered indifferently, that they had no ground why they ſhould impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune me in this more then others. To one of them (&amp; he none of the meaneſt) I offred a conference 3
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152178:19"/> ſeverall times touching all the heads of Religion to be debated, whereby the truth of them might be ſolidly fortified, and the falſity refuted, and that in the preſence of the chiefeſt of our Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; which was refuſed by him. To the reſt ſeveral anſwers were given, plainly denying what was requeſted to ſome; to others o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening my ſelf a little, and this as they were more or leſs known to me: But this accident ſomtimes befel me, that whatever I mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to any, 'twas preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to others, although in the delivery it was judged Orthodox, and their Faith ingaged not to divulge it.</p>
            <p>It's neceſſary that I alſo add what paſſed by Letters the utmoſt confines of our own Nation, <hi>viz.</hi> when in the Preparatory Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention at the <hi>Hag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, June</hi> 1607. by the Summons of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Lords, the States General, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated by the COLLEDGE of BRETHREN, I was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152178:20"/> friendly deſired to make known my thoughts in the buſineſs of Religion to the ſaid Colledge, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging to do their utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſatisfie me, I ſhould utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe ſo to do. Now being ſenſible what a great deal of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie the matter thus related hath created me with many who thought greater honour due to this Aſſembly from me, being congregated from all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, I think my ſelf obliged to give a more perfect account of it.</p>
            <p>Before my departure from <hi>Leyden</hi> to this Convention at the <hi>Hague,</hi> there came to my hands five Articles appertaining to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, diſperſed in ſome Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, read by ſome Miniſters in their Eccleſiaſtick Conventions, &amp; judged by them as containing my Judgement in thoſe points of Religion.</p>
            <p>The Articles were concerning Predeſtination, the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> Free-will, Original Sin, and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152178:20"/> Eternal Salvation of Infants, which when I had thoroughly peruſed, I eaſily perceived by the Author of them whom I then ſpoke, being there preſent, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying freely to him, that I had ground to believe thoſe <hi>Articles</hi> proceeded from him, which he not obſcurely confeſſing, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That they were not ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad as mine, but as points con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted amongſt the Students at <hi>Leyden:</hi> To which I Reply'd, He wel knew that what ever was but lightly divulged this way would greatly prejudice my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, and the <hi>Articles</hi> be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon me, which I there o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly profeſſed never iſſued from me, neither did they agree with my judgement, neither (as far as I could judge) with the word of God.</p>
            <p>Things thus paſſing 'twixt him and me in the preſence of two Witneſſes I judged it requiſite to mention the ſame in the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion becauſe of theſe perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152178:21"/> preſent who had read the <hi>Articles,</hi> ſuppoſing them to be mine (as ſome of them confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to mee) which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly I did. The <hi>Convention</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to diſſolve, their acts and proceedings regiſter'd, and ſome of the Members injoined to give an account thereof to the <hi>Lords, the States General,</hi> I moved the Brethren they would be pleaſed to ſtay a little, having ſomething to offer to them; which they conſenting to, I told them the <hi>five Articles</hi> (then in my hands, the tenor of which I briefly read to them) I had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly found to be ſent abroad into ſeveral <hi>Provinces,</hi> as <hi>Zealand</hi> and the <hi>Dioceſſe</hi> of <hi>Utrecht,</hi> by ſome of this Aſſembly, and read by ſome Miniſters in their publike Meetings, and look't up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as comprehending my Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I there ſolemnly with a good conſcience in the preſence of God, and before all that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention profeſſed, that theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152178:21"/> points of Religion were not mine, neither did they contain <hi>my judgement;</hi> and this I repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted over and over again, humbly beſeeching the brethren, they would not ſo eaſily credit thoſe flying reports of me, neither ſo lightly entertain that as coming from me, diſperſed ſo much to my prejudice.</p>
            <p>To this anſwer was made by one of the <hi>Convention,</hi> I ſhould do wel to ſignifie to the brethren what I approved, or diſliked in thoſe <hi>Articles,</hi> whereby they might come to ſome knowledge of my judgement; which motion was ſeconded by ſome one. But I returned, this <hi>Convention</hi> was not ſummoned for any ſuch end; that we had ſit long enough; and that the <hi>Lords the States</hi> expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted an anſwer: And thus we diſſolved, no man urging it any further, or teſtifying their joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſent by any perſwaſive to the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152178:22"/> reaſonableneſs of it; Nay, ſome there preſent gave out, as I after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward underſtood, that they had it in <hi>ſpecial command</hi> not to enter a debate of any <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which if it had fallen out, they would preſently have deſerted the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention;</hi> and therefore the ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of me herein was far from being the minde of the whole <hi>Aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is a true relation,</hi> Moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Potent States of my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ſolicitation and my refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, whence in my opinion its clearly manifeſt, if reſpect be had <hi>to their requeſt</hi> and the <hi>manner</hi> of it <hi>to my deniall,</hi> and the <hi>ground</hi> thereof, together with my <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments</hi> herein, there was no cauſe for this my accuſation. <hi>Their requeſt</hi> leading to a <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of my ſelf in the matters of faith was not in my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion grounded upon the leaſt reaſon, having never admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152178:22"/> cauſe to them (by teaching that at any time oppugnant <hi>to the Word of God, the Confeſſion or Catec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſme of the Belgick Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi>) why they ſhould deſire this of me more then any other, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving often avouched my readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to give way (if any fruit ſhal be judged likely to come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) that this ſhould be inquired into in a Synod either Provincial or National, that a further knowledge may be had thereof.</p>
            <p>The manner of their Deſire by <hi>Deputies</hi> did manifeſtly diſlike me, being much oppreſſed with the prejudice of the Synod which is not preſumed to ſolicite any man to a conference by their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, without cauſe given them ſo to do; therefore 'twas not ſafe to admit of any ſuch thing, leſt by that means I ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my ſelf guilty of teaching ſomething contrarie to what was right.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152178:23"/>
               <head>Reaſons of my refuſal were theſe.</head>
               <p>Firſt, not being under the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>South</hi> or <hi>North-Holland,</hi> but having other Superiours of my owne, to whom I ſtood bound to give an account of my actions, I could not conſent to any confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with their <hi>Deputies,</hi> unleſs with their conſent, and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs command from them; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially it being <hi>incumbent</hi> not as a <hi>private duty</hi> upon me, the <hi>Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties themſelves</hi> clearly enough in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating the <hi>Conference</hi> not to be of a private nature, in denying to lay aſide the Title of <hi>Deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and proceed in their owne names with me. And therefore I had ſinned againſt my <hi>Superiors</hi> if I had not refuſed the ſame. I wiſh their <hi>Brethren</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, there was never yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Miniſters (ſubjected as a <hi>Member</hi> to their <hi>reſpective Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod</hi>)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152178:23"/> durſt at any time enter a conference without the advice of the Magiſtrate, neither ever any particular Magiſtrate permit the Miniſter under his Juriſdiction to undertake a conference with the Deputies of the <hi>Churches,</hi> unleſs they had firſt conſented to it, which they would often do by being preſent themſelves by their <hi>Deputies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let them onely recollect what was done at <hi>Leyden</hi> in the cauſe<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nomina Locorum Gouda,</hi> Horna Meden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicus.</note> of <hi>Colhaſius</hi> at <hi>Gouda,</hi> with <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus Herberts</hi> at <hi>Horn,</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Cornelius Wigyer</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denblich</hi> in the cauſe of <hi>Taco.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second Reaſon</hi> diſſwading me from the <hi>conference,</hi> was the great inequality thereof; equality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a neceſſary qualification in perſonal debates. 1. They came againſt me (with whom all things ſtood in a private capacity arm'd with publick Authority: Now I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152178:24"/> am not ignorant how greatly they are under-propt, who do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing by vertue of this power. 2. They were three in number, beſides the two deputed from the Synod of <hi>North-Holland</hi> with them; I was alone, not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of help, but alſo of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, to whom (as they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) I might ſafely commit my affairs. 3. They were not at Liberty, being compelled to hang upon the judgment of their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, therefore ſtrictly obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to contend to the utmoſt for that opinion in Religion they were of, inſomuch as 'twas not ſafe for them to admit of my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or arguments, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo cogent and inſoluble; which conſidered, I did not ſee what fruit or advantage could mutually reſult from this confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as in equity ſhould, and which on my part was likely to do, being free in my ſelf, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (by bringing my conſcience
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152178:24"/> in, without the ppejudice of any, to the examination) to admit of that which my conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the Truth, ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate to be right. Of how great concernment all theſe things are your Highneſs's had known more fully, if you had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by your <hi>Deputies</hi> in that <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory Convention.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third Reaſon.</hi> Their own rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after the conference to the Synod, could not but be divers wayes prejudicial to me, whether abſent or preſent; if abſent, it might eaſily happen (either by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, addition, or diſlocation of words, by inconſiderateneſs in defect of underſtanding, or imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility in the want of memory, or by the prejudice of diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) a <hi>Narrative</hi> ſhould be made otherwiſe then the truth of the thing required. If preſent, 'twere difficult to eſcape or correct this inconvenience, better credit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152178:25"/> likely to be given to their <hi>own Deputies,</hi> then to my ſelf a <hi>private perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> By this means I ſhould have yeelded the <hi>Convention</hi> ſome <hi>right</hi> and <hi>prerogative</hi> over mee, which it neither hath, nor I could give, conſidering <hi>my place,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out injuring thoſe our common <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> would ſet over me.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Equitie</hi> did not more conſtrain me, then <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> to repudiate this conference; yet might they have obtained their deſire, if they would have imbraced a private <hi>Debate</hi> of all the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> offered them; this being more accommodate to a mutual <hi>edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> where every one (as the manner is) may ſpeak with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and familiarity, then the other where the Formalities of <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utations</hi> are obſerved: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was there the leaſt ground why they ſhould ſhew themſelves
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152178:25"/> ſo hard to be intreated in this caſe, when every one might have done it himſelf; having further delivered my mind herein, that whatever ſhould be tranſacted by us ſhould abide with us, and not paſs abroad to any; which if they had conſented to, I doubt not but we had either ſatisfied one another, or at laſt made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that no damage could ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue upon this our <hi>mutual contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie</hi> to the <hi>Truth neceſſary to ſalvation, godlineſs, or chriſtian peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To omit theſe things, I cannot give an account to my ſelf how theſe rumours are conſiſtent one with another; I am complain'd of for not declaring my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet in my own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and forraign parts I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh'd againſt, as if I indeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the introduction of ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure Novel and falſe Tenents in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:152178:26"/>
               <p>If I declare not my judgment, whence is the unſoundneſs of it manifeſt? If I explicate not my ſelf, how can I bring in any fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities? If they be nothing but ſuſpitions obtruded upon me, it's againſt the rule of Charity to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſo much to them: But I am reported to expreſs my ſelfe in ſome things, but not in all; yet even in them it's not darkly manifeſt whither I tend. That's to be here obſerved, whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing delivered by me be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>contrary to the Word of God,</hi> or <hi>the Confeſsion of the Belgick Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> If the laſt <note n="*" place="margin">Not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the Belgick Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> be proved, that I have taught any thing contrary to that I ingaged my ſelf by my own ſubſcription, I am liable to puniſhment; if the firſt <note n="*" place="margin">Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Word of God.</note> be made good, I ought to be much more ſtrictly dealt with, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged either to recant or to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide my place, eſpecially if the heads of doctrine were notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly injurious to the honour of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152178:26"/> God, and ſalvation of men. But if they were found neither to claſh with the <hi>Word of God,</hi> nor the <hi>Belgick Confeſsion,</hi> neither the inferences depending upon them, according to the Rule of the Schoolmen, <hi>The conſequences of a doctrine being falſe, the doctrine is falſe likewiſe, and ſo on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> One of theſe ought to have been done, either a charge brought in againſt me, or a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crediting the reports of me: The later I wiſhed for; the firſt I fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not, notwithſtanding the one and thirty <hi>Articles</hi> diſperſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where under my name, to the great prejudice of me, were noted by perſons of great quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, into whoſe hands they were given, with what unſavourineſs they were framed; with what <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> they were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon me: But I expect to hear, <hi>Why did you not to avoyd theſe commotions, and to ſatisfie ſo many Miniſters, fully open your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152178:27"/> ſelfe to your fellow-brethren in the whole matter of Religion, either for your own timely inſtruction, or their ſeaſonable preparation to a mutuall conference?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three inconveniences deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me from this: Leaſt</p>
               <p>Firſt, my judgment profeſſed, ſhould afford matter to them to frame an Action againſt me.</p>
               <p>2. Leaſt the ſame ſhould be diſquieted and refuted in their Pulpits and Academical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes.</p>
               <p>3. Leaſt it ſhould be tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Forraign Univerſities and Churches, with hope of obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a condemnatory ſentence againſt it, and of bearing me down this way; that I had weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cauſe to fear all theſe things, were not hard for me from the Tenents and Writings of ſome of them clearly to demonſtrate. That which reſpects my Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152178:27"/> or inſtruction, which I might hope from thence, ſo it is; there being beſides my ſelfe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others who had drawn up their meditations in the matters of Religion; inſtruction could not ſo profitably be adminiſter'd any where as in the place of our joynt appearance, where a Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive Sentence as they call it, might and ought to be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; as for my brethrens ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Preparation to the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, certainly it would be Then moſt commodious <hi>When every one</hi> have produced their meditations together, and ſo the reaſon of all things at once might be had.</p>
               <p>And thus I have waſhed away the things chiefly caſt upon me, and come to diſcharge my promiſe and execute the commands which you my Lords the Noble and Potent <hi>Sates</hi> have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152178:28"/> laid upon me, being confident hence no prejudice will ariſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to my perſon, or judgment, in that obedience ariſeth from it, which next after God, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God, I owe to this hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Aſſembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>firſt and chief b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anch</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> upon which I have fixed my thoughts for theſe many years laſt paſt, is <hi>the Predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God.</hi> That is, <hi>the election and reprobation of men to life and death;</hi> making my <hi>entrance</hi> here, Ile firſt explain what ſome have delivered in our Churches, and this Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Leyden,</hi> both in words and writings concerning it; then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting my thoughts upon that, I wil laſtly proceed to a <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of my own judgment in this point.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Teachers</hi> in our Churches are not at oneneſs and ſimplicity in their judgments touching this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152178:28"/> 
                  <hi>doctrine,</hi> but various and different amongſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>The opinion of thoſe who take the high and rigid way (as 'tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where contained in their writings) is this,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God by an eternal and immutable decree <hi>out of men,</hi> not conſidered as <hi>made,</hi> much leſs as <hi>fallen,</hi> hath predeſtinated ſome to everlaſting life, others to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deſtruction, without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuition, or <hi>reſpect</hi> to <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> or <hi>ſin, obedience</hi> or <hi>diſobedience,</hi> of his pure <hi>good pleaſure,</hi> to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the glory of his juſtice and mercy, (or, as others) his ſaving grace, wiſdome, and moſt free power.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides this decree, God to have fore-appointed ſome certain <hi>means</hi> belonging to the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, and this by an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and unchangeable Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152178:29"/> theſe meanes are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to follow by vertue of the preceding decree, and unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably to lead him that is predeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinated to his fore-appointed end; Some of theſe <hi>Meanes</hi> lying in Common, appertaining joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the decree of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation;</hi> others in ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting each.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Means common to both,</hi> are three: <hi>Firſt,</hi> the <hi>Creation of Man</hi> in the right ſtate of <hi>Originall righteouſneſſe,</hi> or according to the image and likeneſs of God in Righteouſneſs, and holineſs. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,</hi> the <hi>permiſſion</hi> of the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> or the Ordination of <hi>God,</hi> that man ſhould ſin, and become vitious. The <hi>Third,</hi> the loſing or the taking away of Originall Righteouſneſs, and the ſhutting of him up under ſin and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152178:29"/>IIII. For unleſs God had crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome, he had not had upon whom he might beſtow eternall life, and bring upon everlaſting death; had not he created them in righteouſneſs and ſanctitie, God himſelfe had been the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſin, and ſo had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the right of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the praiſe of his Iuſtice, and ſalvation for the honour of his mercy; unleſs they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had ſinned, and by the merit thereof rendered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves guilty of <hi>Death,</hi> there could have been no place to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate either Juſtice or Mercy.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The meanes fore-ordained<note place="margin">Theſe are the ſpecial means.</note> for the putting into execution the decree of election, are theſe three. Firſt, The preordination or the giving of Jeſus Chriſt, a mediatour and <hi>Saviour,</hi> who ſhould purchaſe by his <hi>merit</hi> for all and onely the <hi>Elect,</hi> life and loſt righteouſneſs, and by his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue communicate the ſame. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152178:30"/> Their <hi>vocation</hi> to faith out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, by the word inwardly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by his ſpirit in the mind, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and will by an operation ſo efficacious, that the elect perſon muſt needs aſſent and yeeld obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereunto, in ſo much as he is not in any capacity able not to beleeve this his <hi>Calling,</hi> or not to be obedient thereunto. Hence comes to paſſe their juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and ſanctification, by the blood and ſpirit of Chriſt, and in like manner all their good workes, and this by the ſame forementioned force and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Third meanes to be, is the <hi>Keeping the Elect</hi> in the faith, ſanctitie and zeale of good works, or the donation of the perſeverance to them, whoſe vertue is to be this; that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving and elect perſons do not onely not ſin with that pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and wholeneſs of will, or not fall <hi>Totally</hi> from faith or grace, but they <hi>Cannot</hi> ſin with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152178:30"/> that full bent of mind, neither <hi>Can</hi> they totally, or finally fall away from faith or grace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The two <note n="*" place="margin">Vacotion &amp; perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</note> laſt of theſe means belonging onely to the adult elect, perſon of ripe years, but for the children of beleevers who paſs out of this life, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to maturity of age, God leads them a ſhorter way to ſalvation, if they belong to the number of the elect (which God onely knows) by giving Chriſt a Saviour to them, and them to Chriſt, who ſaves them by his blood and holy ſpirit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out actuall faith and perſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and this according to the promiſe of the Covenant, <hi>I will be your God and the God of your ſeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>The means</hi> appointed to<note place="margin">Theſe proper to the decree of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation.</note> put into execution the decree of reprobation, are partly proper to <hi>All</hi> the reject and reprobate, (whether they have lived to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152178:31"/> ripeneſs of years, or died before their maturity) partly peculiar to <hi>Some</hi> of them onely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Means Common</hi> to them all, is, their diſſertion in ſin, by the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of that ſaving grace, which is ſufficient and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſalvation; and this hath two branches. 1. God not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing that Chriſt ſhould die for them, neither <note n="*" place="margin">(<hi>i. e.</hi>) He neither <hi>dignitate pretii</hi> died for them, in regard of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the price: <hi>Nor volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiti,</hi> God never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that hee ſhould ſhed his blood for them.</note> 
                  <hi>Quoad Voluntatem Antecedentem,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his <hi>Antecedent</hi> will, (as ſome call it) or <hi>Quoad Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientem,</hi> according to the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient or the valew of that recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliatory Price, which was never offerd for the Reprobate, either in reſpect of the divine decree, or the vertue, and efficacy of it. The 2. branch, Gods unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to communicate the ſpirit of Chriſt to them, without which 'twere impoſſible for them to be made partakers of him and his benefits.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>The means Peculiar to ſome of</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152178:31"/> them onely, is that obduration which befalls <hi>Adult perſons,</hi> for their often &amp; enormous violation of the <hi>Law of God,</hi> &amp; repudiation of the <hi>Grace</hi> of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>To the executing the firſt <note n="*" place="margin">For their violation of the law of God.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duration appertains the witneſs of their minds to the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Law, by knowledge, illumination and conviction, it not being poſſible for the Law, not to detaine them in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs onely, but neceſſary to the rendring them inexcuſable.</p>
               <p>To the execution of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <note n="*" place="margin">For their refuſing the grace of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</note> obduration, God makes uſe of their calling by the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, which is to be both inſufficient and ineffectuall as well in regard of the decree of God, as the event thereof. <hi>This vocation</hi> is to be either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall onely, which they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will nor can obey, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall whereby ſome of them are raiſed in their underſtandings to embrace and beleeve the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152178:32"/> things they heare, yet with ſuch a faith as the devils endowed with, beleeve and tremble; ſome of them are carried on further, even after a manner to deſire to taſte of the <hi>Heavenly Gift,</hi> theſe being the moſt miſerable of all, who are therefore taken up on high, that their fall may be the greater; it being impoſſible that this event ſhould not befall them, neceſſitated to returne to their <hi>vomit,</hi> and to fall away from the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. From this decree of electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reprobation divine, and the adminiſtration of the means appertaining to the execution of both; it followes, that the elect ſhould <hi>neceſſarily</hi> be ſaved, ſo as they are not in any poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of periſhing, and the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates <hi>unavoidably</hi> damned; ſo as 'tis utterly impoſſible for them to be ſaved, and that out of the <hi>abſolute</hi> purpoſe of Gods prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all things and cauſes, which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152178:32"/> are in things, or could reſult from things.</p>
               <p>This Opinion by ſome of thoſe that adhere thereunto, is judged the foundation of <hi>Chriſtianity, Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vation,</hi> and the <hi>certainty</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in which the ſure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted conſolation of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers (giving them a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſcience) is founded; and upon which the praiſe of the grace of God leaneth, in ſo much, as the contradicting this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is ſurely to rob God of the glory of his grace, to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the merit of ſalvation to the free-will and power of man, which ſavours of <hi>Pelagianiſme,</hi> theſe being the cauſes pretended why they labour ſo anxiouſly to retaine the purity of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in their churches, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to all alterations repugnant there unto.</p>
               <p>For my part, to ſpeake what I thinke freely (with the Salvage of a better judgement) I am of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152178:33"/> that minde, That this doctrine of predeſtination containeth in it many things falſe, imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and diſcrepant with it ſelfe, which Univerſally to run thorough time permits me not, but I ſhal leave it to be examind in groſſe in its latitude. There<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> are foure ſpeciall heads in my view; and thoſe of the greateſt weight in this doctrine; I ſhall firſt declare them, then give you my own judgement concerning them; They are theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That God hath <hi>Abſolutely</hi> and preciſely decreed the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome particular men by his mercy or grace, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of others by his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, without any ſight or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuition in this decree of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or ſin; obedience, or diſobedience; that might proceed from either of them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That God, for the bringing to paſſe this his prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding decree, determined the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152178:33"/> of <hi>Adam,</hi> and all men in him, in the right ſtate of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall righteouſneſs, and futher ordained, that they ſhould ſin, and ſo be deprived of originall righteouſneſs, and become guilty of eternall condemnation.</p>
               <p>3. That God hath decreed thoſe (whom he would preciſely ſave) as to ſalvation, ſo to the means appertaining thereunto, to bring them to faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and perſeverance in it; and this indeed by his irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grace, and power, ſo as they cannot but beleeve, perſevere, and be ſaved.</p>
               <p>4. That God hath decreed to deny unto them whom in his abſolute will he hath preordained to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and accordingly doth not confer that grace which is ſufficient and neceſſary to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo as they are neither able to believe neither can they be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Now after the diligent weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and examination of theſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152178:34"/> foure branches in my own breaſt, I come to deliver the things that<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Arminius</hi> his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the doctrine contained in the four branches mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above.</note> follow touching this doctrine of predeſtination.</p>
               <p>1. That this doctrine is not the foundation of <hi>Chriſtianity, Salvation,</hi> or the <hi>Certainty</hi> therof:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Not of Chriſtianity.</head>
               <p>1. For this predeſtination is not that decree of God wherein Chriſt is eſtabliſhed by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Saviour, head and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of thoſe who are made heires of eternall life, which is the onely fundamental of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianity. 2. Neither is this of predeſtination that doctrine, by which men (as living ſtones) are built upon Chriſt alone the corner ſtone by faith, and joyned to him as members to the head.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Not of ſalvation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. For this predeſtination is not that decree of the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God in Chriſt Jeſus, upon which alone our ſalvation lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, 2. It is no foundation of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152178:34"/> Salvation, for it is not the powor of God unto ſalvation to thoſe that beleeve, in that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God is not manifeſted by it, <hi>ex fide in fidem,</hi> from faith to faith. Neither of the certainty of ſalvation. For that ſtayeth it ſelfe upon this decree, they that beleeve ſhall be ſaved; I beleeve, therefore I ſhall be ſaved; but this doctrine of predeſtination neither comprehendeth the firſt, or ſecond member of this ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, which ſome confeſſed in theſe words, <hi>We meane not that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conſult the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> 
                  <hi>the knowing of this (predeſtination) is the foundation of Chriſtianity or ſalvation; or that it is neceſſary after the ſame manner, as the doctrine of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly; The doctrine of<note place="margin">2 Arg.</note> predeſtination thus delivered, doth not contain in it either the whole or any part of the Goſpel; for this conſiſts partly of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of faith, and repentance; partly of a promiſe of forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152178:35"/> of ſins, of the ſpirit of grace, and of eternal life, according to the tenure of the ſermons of Chriſt and the Baptiſt his forerunner, and his ſucceſſours the Apoſtles, after his aſcention; but this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination neither reſpects the command of faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, neither the promiſe; it doth not teach us What kind of perſons God hath predeſtinated in general, which is properly the Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical doctrine, but contains in it a myſtery (onely known to God) wherein are comprehended the individual perſons whom God hath decreed to ſave and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne; whence I further conclude this doctrine of predeſtination not to be neceſſary, either to be known, beleeved, hoped in, or effected, to ſalvation; ſo a learned man confeſſeth in his queſtions to bee diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; <hi>Why, the Goſpel cannot be termed a Book, or diſcovery of predeſtination</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſimply in its
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152178:35"/> ſelf, but</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>reſpectively, becauſe it neither Sets downe the numerical matter nor forme, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, that is, It doth not declare how many, nor whom</hi> (<note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> whom God knew before he came out of the womb, &amp; ſanctified him, <hi>Jer. 5</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>a very few onely excepted) but what kind of perſons in general are predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly; This doctrine of predeſtination was never ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, decreed, or approved<note place="margin">3 Arg.</note> of for the firſt ſix hundred yeares after Chriſt; in any councel,<note place="margin">General Councils.</note> either general, or particular; not in the Councel holden at <hi>Nice,</hi> wherein it was determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt <hi>Arrius,</hi> for the diety and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Son of God; not in the firſt at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in which it was decreed againſt <hi>Macedonius,</hi> for the diety of the holy Ghoſt; not in the <hi>Epheſine</hi> Councel againſt <hi>Neſtorius</hi> for the unity of the perſon of the Son of God; not in that holden at <hi>Calcedon,</hi> which condemned <hi>Eutiches,</hi> and determined for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152178:36"/> two diſtinct natures in one and the ſame perſon of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; not in the ſecond held at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in which <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch, Anthym</hi> the <hi>Conſtantinopoletane,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were condemned for aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the paſſion of the Father with the Son; not in the third at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in which the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothelites</hi> were condemned for affirming to be but one only will and operation in Jeſus Chriſt. Neither had this doctrine any better intertainment in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Councils, as that at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Particular Councils.</note> 
                  <hi>Arauſin;</hi> neither was it vinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated or confirmed in that held at <hi>Milevite,</hi> in Affrick, againſt <hi>Pelagius</hi> and his errors, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the Articles of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine decreed in it againſt them.</p>
               <p>And the doctrine of <hi>Auſtine</hi> himſelfe touching this point was ſo farre from being received in theſe Councils that <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Romane biſhop, his contempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152178:36"/> writing to the biſhops of France, and condemning the Pelagion tenents ſhuts up his Epiſtle in theſe words, As we dare not contemne, the more profound and difficult parts of thoſe queſtions ſtarted and broadly handled by the oppoſers of the Hereticks; ſo judge we it not neceſſaty to abet them, beleeving it ſufficient what the writings have taught us according to the forementioned rules of the apoſtolical ſeat, to the owning of the grace of God from whoſe power and worth nothing ought to be ſubſtracted. For thoſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons mentioned by <hi>Celeſtine</hi> in his Epiſtle, and decreed in the three foregoing particular Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, we ſhall agree well enough, eſpecially as to thoſe things which were requiſite for the maintaining of grace againſt <hi>Pelagius</hi> and his errours.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, There was never<note place="margin">4 Arg.</note> any ſound, and orthodox teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152178:37"/> of the church for 600. yeares next after Chriſt, that ever broched and approved this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of predeſtination, no not the keeneſt aſſertors of Grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Pelagius;</hi> ſuch was <hi>Jerome, Auſtin,</hi> the Author of the Book entituled, <hi>The Call of the Gentiles, Prosper, the Aquitani, Hilarius, Fulgentius, Oroſius,</hi> as appears by their writings.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, This holds no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">5 Arg.</note> or correſpondency with the Harmony of Confeſſions put forth in the name of all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and Proteſtant Churches, Printed and publiſhed at <hi>Geneva.</hi> For if they be faithfully conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 'twill be apparently manifeſt, that many of them do not agree in this point, ſome of them onely glancing at it. And as to the four heads above-mentioned, chiefly urged in this Doctrine, not once touched upon by them, no Confeſsion of any <hi>Reformed</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152178:37"/> church, delivering the doctrine of predeſtination, as before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by me. The <hi>Bohemian Confeſſion,</hi> the confeſſion of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that of <hi>Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge,</hi> the firſt <hi>Helv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tian confeſſion</hi> of the foure Cities, <hi>Argentorate, Conſtantia, Memminga,</hi> and <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davia,</hi> make not the leaſt menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it. The <hi>Baſilian</hi> and that of <hi>Saxony</hi> do onely point at it in three words. The <hi>Auguſtan</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is ſo darke, that it ſtands in need of annotations to pread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh us of it, as they of <hi>Geneva</hi> have thought; the laſt <hi>Helvetian confeſſion,</hi> which hath the conſent and ſubſcription of the greateſt part of all reformed churches, doth ſo ſpeak of it that I would gladly ſee how it is conſiſtent w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> it as before repreſented; though the <hi>Sabaudican</hi> and that at <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi> have approved it.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Without all ſtrife and<note place="margin">6. Arg.</note> contention this doctrine may be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152178:38"/> juſtly cald into queſtion touching its concordancy with the <hi>Belgick Confeſſion,</hi> and <hi>Heydelberg Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> as I ſhall briefly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. <hi>Artic. 14. Confeſ. Belg.</hi> you have this paſſage, <hi>Man knowingly and willingly ſubjected himſelf to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor proves the diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine with the <hi>Belgick</hi> Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being that of his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, rather then any other.</note> 
                  <hi>ſin, and by conſequence to Death and Malediction, whileſt he inclined his ear to the words and impoſtures of the Devil.</hi> Whence I conclude, Man ſinned not by any neceſſity of the preceding Decree of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is diametrically op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Doctrine thereof. Again, <hi>Artic.</hi> 16. ſpeaking of the Eternal Election of God; <hi>God ſhewed himſelf mercifull by ſaving and freeing them from damnation, whom in his everlaſting and unchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable counſel for his gracious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without any reſpect of works, he choſe in his Son Chriſt Ieſus our Lord; and alſo juſt in relinquiſhing others in that their fall and perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereinto they had precipitated themſelves.</hi> How theſe words are
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152178:38"/> conſiſtent with the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctrine, I plainly ſee not.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Heydelberg Catechiſm, Queſt. 20. Salvation is not given to all thoſe by Chriſt who periſhed in Adam; but to them onely who are ingrafted into him by faith, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his benefits.</hi> Whence I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude God to have fore-appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed none abſolutely to Salvation, but thoſe beheld in his Decree as believers; which is in open defiance with the firſt and third head of this Predeſtination. So <hi>Queſt.</hi> 54.<note place="margin">See pag. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>I believe the Son of God out of all Mankinde doth from the beginning unto the end of the World gather a choſen company conſenting in the true faith unto Eternal life;</hi> Where Election to life and conſent in Faith are mutually placed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the latter not ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to the former, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ought neceſſarily to have
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152178:39"/> been; and the words run thus, <hi>The Son of God calls and gathers by his ſpirit and word a company choſen unto life everlaſting, that they might believe and agree in the faith.</hi> Things being thus, there is no cauſe why the maintainers and promoters of this Doctrine ought with that violence contend to obtrude the ſame on their Complices, or the Church of Chriſt, or take it in ſuch ill part when any thing is taught either in Church or Univerſity, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, or at variance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>Seventhly; This Doctrine<note place="margin">7. Arg.</note> fights againſt the very Nature of God; eſpecially with thoſe Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of his Divine Being, by which he worketh and manageth all things, <hi>viz.</hi> With his Wiſdom, Juſtice and Goodneſs. It oppoſeth his Wiſdom three waies; 1. In that it aſſerteth God to decree ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for that end, which neither
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152178:39"/> is good, nor can be made ſo; ſuch is Gods creation of ſome perſons to eternal Perdition to the praiſe of his Juſtice. 2. In that it aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth God by this Predeſtination to have propoſed to himſelf the demonſtration of the praiſe of his Mercy and Juſtice: which he could no way do but by an act contrary to both; ſuch is that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree whereby he determined that man ſhould ſin and become miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. 3. It changetk and invert's the order &amp; method of the two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Wiſdom of God, manifeſt in Scripture, in that it aſſerts God abſolutely to have fore-appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſalvation of men by the Mercy and Wiſdom comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Doctrine of the Croſs of Chriſt; without foreſeeing 'twas impoſſible that man, and that through his own default, ſhould be ſaved, by Wiſdom per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the Lavv, and infuſed into him by Creation, vvhen the Scripture avers the contrary,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152178:40"/> 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 1. It pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſs of Preaching, to ſave thoſe that believe,</hi> [i. e.] <hi>By the Word of the Croſs, after that in the Wiſdom of God the world by wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knew not God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 It wars againſt the Juſtice of God, which repreſents him not only as a Lover of Righteouſneſs and hater of ſin, but as having a perpetual and unſhaken will of giving every one his right: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt of theſe, in that it makes God preciſely to will the ſalvation of ſingular men, and decree the ſame without any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuition or reſpect to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or obedience, and become a lover of thoſe men more then his own Juſtice. Againſt the later, in that it ſtateth Gods vvillingneſs to entail miſery upon the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (which is onely the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin) not beholding it as peccant, and ſo a culpable ſubject of Wrath and Puniſhment, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152178:40"/> ſo is made to impoſe upon the creature both that which belongs not unto it, &amp; likewiſe that which is in conjuction with its greateſt evil, which is abhorrent from his Juſtice. According therefore to this Doctrine, God firſt detracts from himſelf that which is his right, and attributes to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that which appertains not unto it, to the making of it miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is in open defiance with the goodneſſe of God, which is an affection in him of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating good according to that fitneſſe and congruity, judged and permitted by his Juſtice. But in this Doctrine of Predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God is ſet forth unto us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced of his own accord, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any external Motive, to will and ordain the greateſt evil to the Creature, and that by an eternal preordination, preceding any determination in him of indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152178:41"/> it with the leaſt good, this Doctrine being a declaration of Gods will to damn, which that he might execute, he purpoſed alſo to create; now Creation is the firſt egreſſe of Divine goodneſſe: How diſcrepant are theſe things from that bounty of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth good, not only to the undeſerving, but alſo evil and guilty perſons, and which we are commanded to imitate in our heavenly Father?</p>
               <p>Eightly, It oppugneth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note place="margin">8. Arg.</note> of man, conſider'd in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing created after the Image of God, in knowledge and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, in freedom of will, with aptitude and affection to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Eternal life. Theſe three things may be concluded of him out of of that ſhort ſentence, <hi>Do this, and live; in the day thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 5 Gen. 2. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>that, thou ſhalt dye.</hi> If any of theſe be taken away from him, the force and weight of that moniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152178:41"/> exciting him to obedience, falls to the ground.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It oppoſeth the Image of God in man, conſiſting in ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and knowledge of him, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to which man was apt, able, &amp; obliged to know, love, worſhip, and ſerve God; but by this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination, intervening, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prevening, man was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained That he ſhould be viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſinful; [<hi>i. e.</hi>] That he ſhould not know God, love, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or ſerve him; neither per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that which according to the Image of God in his aptitude, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie, and obligement, he ſtood bound to do, which <hi>tant.</hi> amounts this, That God created man after his own Image in holineſs and righteouſneſs, but fore-ordained and decreed, That man ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come impure, injuſt; [<hi>i. e.</hi>] be made conformable to the Satani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Image.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152178:42"/>2. This doctrine combats the liberty of mans will, with which he was inveſted by his creation, in that it impedes and hinders the uſe and exerciſe thereof by binding up and determining the ſame to one part, in the doing this or that; ſo that one of theſe two, God (which be far from us to think) muſt be guilty of, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that he created man with freedom of will, or hindred him in the exerciſe thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus created; the firſt chargeth him with incogitancy, the laſt with mutability, and both with being iniurious to man and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It's prejudiciall to man, in regard of that propenſity, and capacity implanted in him by his creation for the enioyment of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life, in as much as by this predeſtinatory decree it is fore-appointed, that the greater part of men ſhall not partake of eternall bliſs, but fall into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152178:42"/> condemnation, and that before the ordinance was paſſed in heaven for their creation, they are deprived of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying their innate inclinations, thoſe concreated tendencies to life ingrafted in them by the hand of their Creator, and that not by their own preceding ſinne and merit, but ſimply and alone by this Predeſtination.</p>
               <p>Ninethly, This Predeſtination<note place="margin">9. Arg.</note> is diametrically repugnant to the act of Creation; For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Creation is the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Creation is made a means to put in to Execution the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees.</note> of good, according to the intrinſecal propriety of its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but ſuch a Creation as hath this intent and meaning, that it may be a way by which Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion formerly made might attain its end, is not the communication of good; all good is to be eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and judged of according to the mind of the giver, or the end to, or for which it was given.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152178:43"/> The intent of the Donor here had been damnation, which muſt have the creature for its ſubject; the end or event of this Creation, the eternal perdition thereof; in which caſe Creation had not been the communication of any good, but a preparatory to the greateſt evil, and that both according to the intent of the Creator, and the event of the thing, according to that of our Saviour, <hi>It had been</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>better for that man that he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been born.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Reprobation</hi> ſavours of hatred, &amp; ariſeth from thence; but <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> cannot proceed of hatred; therefore it is no <hi>way</hi> or <hi>means</hi> appertaining to the execution thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Creation is a perfect act of God, a declarative of his Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Omnipotencie; therefore not ſubordinate to the end of any precedaneous Work or action of God; but rather is to be looked upon as an act appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152178:43"/> neceſſarily antecedaneous, and preceding all other actions, which he either could decree or undertake; for without the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conception of it, he could not ordain the actual undertaking of any other buſineſs; without its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution he could not abſolve and finiſh any other Work.</p>
               <p n="4">4. All the actions of God, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the damnation of his creatures, are aliens and forraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in that God conſents unto them for ſome other extraneous cauſe; but Creation is the moſt proper act of God, to which he could not be moved by any exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal cauſe, being that firſt act of God, without which indeed there is nothing elſe but God, every thing that now is having its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by this action.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If Creation be the way or <hi>means</hi> by which God will execute the Decree of his Reprobation, then he wills more the act of REPROBATION, then
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152178:44"/> that of creation, &amp; pleaſeth himſelf<note place="margin">That wch a man wils as the means, muſt needs be leſs conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by him then that which he wills as the end. <hi>Arminius</hi> meaneth Elect and reprobate perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both in <hi>Adam</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> more in the act of condemning ſome of his harmleſs creatures, then in the act of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Creation cannot be a way or means to Reprobation, according to the abſolute pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God; when that being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, man might ſtill remain in obedience to Gods command, and not ſinne, to which God had afforded ſufficient ſtrength on the one part, and placed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable impediments on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is in open hoſtility with this Doctrine of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, This Predeſtination<note place="margin">10. Arg.</note> ſutes not the nature of eternal life, and thoſe Titles wherewith it is dignified in Scripture; its cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Inheritance of the ſons of God;</hi> but thoſe are the onely ſons<note place="margin">Tit. 3. 7.</note>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:152178:44"/> of GOD according to<note place="margin">Joh. 1. 12.</note> the Doctrine of the Goſpel, who believe in the name of <hi>Jeſus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt;</hi> it's further termed, <hi>The reward of obedience, and of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of love, the recompence of thoſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>who have fought a good fight, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>run well, a crown of righteouſneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore God hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned eternal life to any out of his abſolute decree, without any reſpect or conſideration had of faith and obedience.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, This doctrine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agrees with the nature of eternall<note place="margin">11. Arg.</note> death, and thoſe names put upon it by the Holy Ghoſt; it's ſtiled <hi>The wages of ſin; the puniſhment of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23</note> 
                  <hi>eternal deſtruction, which is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1. 8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>for them that know not God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obey the Goſpel of Chriſt; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 25. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>Fire prepared for the Devil and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 27</note> 
                  <hi>his Angels; Fire which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Adverſaries of God:</hi> Therefore everlaſting death is prepared for none out of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute decree of God, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152178:45"/> ſight or intuition of ſin and diſobedience.</p>
               <p>Twelfthly, This doctrine jarrs<note place="margin">12. Arg.</note> with the nature and property of Sin, and that two ways. 1. Sin is known by the names of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and rebellion in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which finds no place in that perſon upon whom an unavoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable neceſſity of ſinning by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the preceding decree of God is incumbent. 2. Sin is the meritorious cauſe of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Now the meritorious cauſe is that which moves the will of God to reprobate according to juſtice; it induceth God to whom ſin is hateful, to reject and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate; therefore ſin can be no middle or intermediate cauſe by which God executeth his decree or will of reprobation.</p>
               <p>13. This predeſtination fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">13 Arg.</note> againſt the very nature of the grace of God, and as much as in it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152178:45"/> lyeth, deſtroys its very being, although it is pretended to bee moſt advantagious and neceſſary for its eſtabliſhment; and this it doth three wayes: Firſt, Grace is accommodated to the nature of man, not aboliſhing the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his will, but rightly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, and correcting its depravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yeelding unto him his proper motions and inclinations; But this Doctrine introduceth ſuch a kind of grace by which the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the will is wholly taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and the exerciſe of it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Secondly, Grace in the Scripture is ſet forth unto us as <hi>reſiſtible, that may bee received in vain, omitted, not aſſented unto, not co-operated with;</hi> this Predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on affirming the contrary, that it is an irreſiſtible force and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Thirdly, <hi>Grace</hi> according<note place="margin">Acts 7. 51. 2 Cor. 6. 1. Heb. 12. 15. Matt. 23. 37. Luk. 7. 30.</note> to the primary intent and minde of God, leads to the good of thoſe to whom it is tendered and received; but this doctrine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152178:46"/> grace to be afforded ſome reprobate perſons, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to the very illumination of their underſtandings, and <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Heavenly Gift,</hi> for no other end and purpoſe, then that being lifted up on high their fall might be the greater, that they might merit and receive the more heavy condemnation.</p>
               <p>14. It's injurious to the glory of<note place="margin">14 Arg.</note> God, which ſtands not in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Liberty or Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, conſiſts not in the demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Wrath and Power; but as it's well conſiſtent with his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, with the honorable ſalvage of his goodneſs; but it ſtrongly reſults from this Doctrine, <hi>That God is the author of ſin</hi> upon this four-fold account.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that it makes God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely to have decreed the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his glory <note n="*" place="margin">Glory by punitive Juſtice, ſuppoſeth a ſubject peccant and cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable; if he decree the end neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, why not the means, ſin and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</note> by punitive Juſtice and Mercy in the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome, and condemnation
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152178:46"/> of others, which neither is, nor ever could be effected but by the entrance of ſin into the world.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that it affirms, God (for the attaining of his end) <note n="*" place="margin">See p. 21. where the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of mans fall is made a means to execute the decree of Predeſt.</note> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that man ſhould ſin and become vitious; by which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God, man's fall was unavoidable.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For that it aſſerts God to have ſubſtracted and denied that grace to man ſufficient and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the avoidance of ſin, and that before his actual tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; which is all one, as if he had impoſed upon his creature a Law impoſſible for him to keep, conſider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in the natural capacity wherein he was created.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe it attributes to God thoſe actious concerning man as well external as internal; mediate (by the intervening of other creatures) as immediate; by which man was neceſſitated to ſin, and that <hi>neceſſitate conſequentis,</hi> by a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152178:47"/> conſequential neceſſity (as the School-men call it) anteceding the thing it ſelf, which is wholly deſtructive to the freedom of mans will; &amp; this act it imputeth to God, as out of his chief &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary intention, without any preſciencie, or fore-knowledge of mans inclination, will, or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Hence may be deducted, <hi>That God truly ſins;</hi> becauſe (according to this Doctrine) he provokes to ſin by an unavoidable act, out of his own purpoſe and primary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, without the leaſt induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the precedent merit and ſin of the creature: It's fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concludable from theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, <hi>That God onely ſins;</hi> it not being competible to that man (being the commiſſion of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden act) who is moved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by force inevitable.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, It follows, <hi>That ſin is no ſin,</hi> it neither being ſo in its ſelf, nor worthy of that Name, which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152178:47"/> God himſelf doth. Beſides theſe, it wounds the honor of God ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way; but for the preſent theſe may ſeem ſufficient to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
               <p>Fifteenthly, This Doctrine is highly ignominious to Chriſt our<note place="margin">15. Arg.</note> Saviour; for, 1. It ſhuts him out<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> pag. 22. where Chriſt is placed as a means to put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Decree of election.</note> of the Decree of Predeſtination, by pre-determining the end, and affirming men were firſt fore-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſalvation; and then Chriſt ordained to ſave them, which removes him from being the foundation of Election. 2. It denies him to be the meritorious cauſe in the recovery of our loſt ſalvation, placing him only as a cauſe ſubordinate to the ſalvation fore-appointed, as a Servant &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to apply the ſame to us: and this holds coreſpondency w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> that opinion wherein God is jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged abſolutely to will the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome men, and that in his firſt and ſupreme Decree (upon which all his other Ordinations
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152178:48"/> depend and follow) ſo that it was impoſſible thoſe men ſhould loſe their ſalvation, and therefore not neceſſary by the merit of Chriſt, preordained a Saviour to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, to be repaired, and as we may ſo ſpeak, found anew, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered for them only.</p>
               <p>Sixteenthly: This Doctrine is<note place="margin">16. Arg.</note> noxious and harmful to the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men: For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It hinders that ſaluteferous and godly ſorrow for ſin, which cannot be found in thoſe who have no remorſe and feeling thereof, which Contrition no man is capable of who commits ſin by the inevitable neceſſity of<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 10.</note> the Decree of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It puts to flight that pious ſolicitude of turning our ſelves from fin to God; for he that is purely paſſive, and like <hi>a dead man,</hi> not only in the preception<note place="margin">Rev. 2. 3.</note> of the preſent Grace of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing him; but alſo in his aſſent
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152178:48"/> and obedience thereunto, and is ſo converted by an irreſiſtible power, that he cannot but feel the pulſes of grace, forced to give up his aſſent thereunto, whereby he is changed, cannot conceive or induce into his minde any ſuch carefulneſs, unleſs he hath firſt felt that irreſiſtible motion; or if at any time he ſhould ſtirre up in his heart any ſuch ſolicitude, it would be fruſtraneous, and of no advantage unto him; for it could not be any true carefulneſs which was not begotten in him by that irreſiſtible force, according to the preciſe purpoſe, and abſolute in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of God for his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It inhibiteth and reſtrains the zeal and ſtudy of good works in converted perſons, when it ſaith regenerate perſons are in no capacity of doing either more or leſs good then they do; for he that is acted by ſaving-grace is obliged to work, neither can he intermit
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152178:49"/> it; but not being agitated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, he can do nothing, he muſt of neceſſity omit it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It extinguiſheth all precato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry zeal and fervencie; Prayer is that efficacious means inſtituted of God for the obtaining of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good thing, eſpecially ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at his hands; but from him who hath determined the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe men, <hi>by an unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and immutable Decree,</hi> Prayer can be no means to procure it; it's onely the Worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God; for out of his poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive decree of Predeſtination he hath appointed the ſalvation of ſuch individual men.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It takes away that wholſome <hi>fear and trembling</hi> in which we are commanded to work out our<note place="margin">Ph. l. 2. 12.</note> ſalvation, in that it poſitively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, That the elect and believing perſon cannot ſin with that full bent of will as the wicked do, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther totally or finally fall away from faith or grace received.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:152178:49"/>6. It begets in men a deſpair of doing that which their duty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, &amp; obtaining that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto their deſires were carried out, when they are taught that the grace of God, which is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the production of every good act, out of the abſolute and preciſe Decree of God, is denied to the major part of men, and that in purſuance of a preceding Decree, equally peremptory with the later, wherein he determined not to confer eternal life, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting death upon them; it cannot but eaſily hence ariſe, that whoever is not perſwaded of his being elected, ſhould judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the number of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, whence muſt needs ſpring up in him a fearful deſparation of doing righteouſneſs, and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eternal life.</p>
               <p>Seventeenthly, This Doctrine<note place="margin">17. Arg.</note> inverts the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. In the Goſpel God
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152178:50"/> requires of men faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, promiſing to converts and believers life everlaſting; but by this Decree of Predeſtination, God is ſet forth as preciſely wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to give ſalvation to ſome ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular men, together with faith and repentance by an abſolute and irreſiſtible power, becauſe 'twas his will and pleaſure to ſave them. In the goſpel God denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth eternal death to Impenitents and Unbelievers, that deterring them by his threats from their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity he might ſave them; but in this Decree of Predeſtination God is repreſented unwilling to give unto ſome men that grace neceſſary to Faith and Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe he had peremptorily decreed to condemn them. The goſpel ſaith, <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely begotten Son,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 Joh. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>that whoſoever believed in him ſhould not periſh, but have everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life:</hi> but this Doctrine ſaith, <hi>God ſo loved thoſe he abſolutely ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152178:50"/> to eternal life, that he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his Son for them alone, and works them up to faith by force irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible.</hi> In a word, the goſpel ſaith, <hi>Perform the Command, and thou ſhalt obtain the Promiſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and thou ſhalt live:</hi> but this Doctrine ſaith, <hi>Becauſe it is my will and pleaſure to beſtow life upon thee, therefore will I give faith unto thee likewiſe;</hi> which is the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the goſpel, and a tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it upſide down</p>
               <p>Eighteenthly, This Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">18. Arg.</note> is in open hoſtility with the Miniſtry of the goſpel.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For no man can be a Minlſter and fellow-labourer with God, neither the Word preached by him an inſtrument of grace and the ſpirit, if the Lord quicken him who is dead in ſin by an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible power, no more then the creature could be an inſtrument of <note n="*" place="margin">Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Grace <hi>i. e.</hi> of love in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world.</note> grace in the firſt Creation or Contributory to its reſuſcitation from the dead.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:152178:51"/>2. By this Doctrine the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Goſpel is made the ſavor of death unto death to the greater part of Auditors, and an inſtrument of condemnation out of the primary purpoſe, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute intent of God, without the leaſt intuition of their preceding Rebellion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By this Predeſtination bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm to reprobate Infants, the children of federal and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Parents, is a meer blank, and ſeals nothing, and ſo altogether unprofitable, and that out of the preciſe Intention of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any default of the Infants, to whom according to divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand this Ordinance is admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This obſtructs faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in publique prayers and ſupplications to God for the benefit of all thoſe that hear the word, when according to this
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152178:51"/> doctrine there are many amongſt them whom God is not onely not willing to ſave, but in his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, eternall &amp; immutable will preceding all things and cauſes, would condemne, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Apoſtle injoining Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſupplications to be made for all men adds this reaſon, <hi>for this is good and acceptable before</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 1, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>God our Saviour, who will have all men to be ſaved, and to come unto the knowledg of the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The compoſure of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine eaſily renders Paſtors and Teachers ſloathfull and negligent in their function, as if their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence were onely advantagious to thoſe whom God would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely ſave, being in no poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of periſhing; and their neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence only Prejudiciall to thoſe whom God would have miſcarry, and are neceſſarily to be undone for ever without any poſſibility of ſalvation.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:152178:52"/>
               <p>19. This Doctrine tends to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions<note place="margin">19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Arg.</note> overthrow in Generall, and the chriſtian in ſpeciall: Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion conſidered in generall, is founded upon a twofold love of God, without which it neither hath nor ever will have any being in the world; the firſt is that <hi>Love of righteouſneſſe,</hi> which gives being to the hatred of ſin; the ſecond is, <hi>the love of the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall creature,</hi> the love extended to man, as in the buſineſſe in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>He that cometh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. ii. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>God muſt believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of thoſe that diligently ſeek him:</hi> his love of righteouſneſſe is demonſtrated in this, that he will not give eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life to any but thoſe that ſeek him; his love of men, that he will beſtow bleſſedneſſe upon them, if they inquire after him. The mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall relation betwixt them is this; There can be no place for the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxes of love to the creature,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152178:52"/> but as the love of righteouſneſſe permits it. <hi>The</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The love of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then the love of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 
                  <hi>former is far more excellent then the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er;</hi> there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a way open for the emana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of love to the Creature, where the love of righteouſneſſe hath not ſtop't it.</p>
               <p>The firſt is evident, in Gods con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning man for ſin, which he loves as his Creature, which he would not do, if man were more dear to him then his own juſtice; or his eternal ruin more abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent then his diſobedience: The ſecond is clear, in that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes none but for ſin, and ſaves thoſe that are turnd from it, which would not be done by him unleſſe he yeelded his love to the Creature ſo far as juſtice regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by judgment permitted it. This Doctrine of predeſtination inverts and changeth this order and mutuall reſpect; Firſt, by aſſerting God preciſely to will the ſalvation of ſome men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having in his purpoſe an eye
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152178:53"/> to their obedience, whereby his love of men is preferd to his love of righteouſneſſe; and that as men, they are more reſpected by him then his own juſtice, and their miſery more abhorrent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, then their ſin and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. The ſecond, by aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the contrary, that God ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely will's the deſtruction of ſome men, no conſideration had in his decree of their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which detract's from his love to the Creature that which appertains to it, and repreſent's a Creature-hatred in God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe or neceſſity drawn from his love of juſtice, and hatred of obliquity; wherein true it is not, that ſin is the primary ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Divine diſpleaſure, and the ſole meritorious cauſe thereof. Of how great importance this is to the razing the foundation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, we may aptly ſee in this ſimilitude; ſuppoſe a child ſpeaking, My father is ſo great a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152178:53"/> lover of juſtice and equity, that if I ſhould be found in waies of diſobedience before him, he would diſinherit me, though his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſon, therefore the duty of obedience is highly incumbent upon me, if I think to be his heir. Another ſaith, My father hath fixed his love ſo much upon me, that he is abſolutely reſolved to make me his heire; what need is there of obedience? for in his immutable Will I am deſtinated to the inheritance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and rather then he will ſuffer me to come ſhort thereof, he will draw me to obey him by force irreſiſtible; which is in a direct line of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the words of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,<note place="margin">Matt. 3. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>And thinke not to ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your ſelves, Wee have</hi> ABRAHAM <hi>to our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for I ſay unto you, God is able of theſe Stones to raiſe up Children unto</hi> ABRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAM.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:152178:54"/>
               <p>The <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> is alſo built upon this double Love, as upon its foundation, though a little otherwaies conſidered then before, according to the change of mans ſtate, who being created in the Image and favour of God, became peccant through his own default, and an enemy to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. The love of Righteouſneſs, upon which our Religion lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, is chiefly that which once he declared only in Chriſt, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould expiate ſin, but <hi>the blood and death of his Son,</hi> neither would he admit him our <hi>Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> and <hi>Interceſſor,</hi> but as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled with his blood. A de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative of this he makes daily in the preaching of the Goſpel, that he will not communicate Chriſt and his benefits to any but thoſe that turn unto and believe in him. The Love to miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, upon which alſo the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion</hi> is bottom'd, is, firſt,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152178:54"/> that by which he hath given <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Son for them, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him the Saviour of them that believe; as alſo that by which he requires obedience, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rigour and ſeverity of his utmoſt right and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but with grace and clemency, and the promiſe of remiſſion of ſin, if ſo be lapſed man repent. This Fundamental the doctrine of Predeſtination encounters two ways: Firſt, by affirming Gods love to be ſo great to ſome Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that he would preciſely ſave them before he had given ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his love of Juſtice in Chriſt Jeſus, and that in his fore-knowledge according to his purpoſe; nay, it overturns the foundation of Chriſtianity, by repreſenting God willing to have his juſtice ſatisfied, becauſe hee would preciſely ſave theſe men; which is to ſubordinate his love of Juſtice, teſtified in Chriſt, to his love of ſinful men, whom he
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152178:55"/> would reſolutely ſave. Secondly, by making God abſolutely wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to damn ſome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſinners, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſideration of their impenitency, when a plenary ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to his love of Juſtice, and hatred of Sin had been given in Chriſt Jeſus; ſo that nothing ſtood in the way of his mercy to be ſhewn unto Sinners, be they what they will, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of repentance; except ſome have a minde to ſay, what is contained in this doctrine of Predeſtination, that God will proceed in greater ſeverity with the major part of men, then hee did with <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and his apoſtate Angels; and that it is his will that Chriſt and the Goſpel profit them no more then the infernal ſpirits; that the gate of mercy is equally ſhut againſt them both; when theſe ſinned in their own perſons out of malice by a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary act, the other in their Parent <hi>Adam,</hi> having no actuall being of themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:152178:55"/>
               <p>To the better underſtanding<note place="margin">A more exact de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the precedent things.</note> how this twofold love is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Religion, and that in the mutual reſpect one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let's ponder more accurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that of the Apoſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>He that cometh unto God must believe that he is, &amp; that he is a rewarder of all thoſe that diligently ſeek him:</hi> In theſe words, two fund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amentals are laid againſt the two fiery darts of Satan, <hi>Security</hi> and <hi>Deſpair,</hi> the pernicious Peſts of Religion, either of them ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the everſion and extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. The firſt flatters a man into the perſwaſion that though he ſerve not God, yet ſhall he not periſh, but obtaine ſalvation. The other renders him confident, that though hee do worſhip and ſerve him, yet ſhall he not get. any remuneration of him; either of theſe exclude all true divine worſhip. An Antidote againſt both, the Apoſtolicall words affords. He that believes
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152178:56"/> God wil give eternal life to thoſe onely that ſeek him, and upon all others inflict everlaſting death, cannot eaſily be ſecure; he that credits God to be a rewarder of thoſe that ſeek him, will not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily deſpair: The ground of the firſt perſwaſion is Gods love of Righteouſneſs, more dear to him then Man himſelf, which ſhakes off ſecurity; The foundation of the other, by which man believes ſtedfaſtly God to be a rewarder of the true ſeekers of him, is that his ſo great love to the Creature Man, that nothing impedes his beſtowing ſalvation on him, but the love which hee bears to his own Juſtice; which is ſo far from being an hindrance, that it doth rather promote and advance it: Upon this account, Man in his diſquiſition and ſearch of God, is not dubious of divine remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and thus diffidence or deſperation is put to flight: If ſo, that this double love, and the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152178:56"/> relation, as hath been clear'd, be Religions foundation, without which it cannot ſubſiſt; then the doctrine repugnant to this love, both abſolute and relative, everts and overthrows the ſame.</p>
               <p>Twentiethly, This Doctrine<note place="margin">20 Arg.</note> of Predeſtination, as well in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, as theſe wherein wee live, ſtands rejected by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the Profeſſors of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. To paſs in ſilence the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges foregoing, things themſelves witneſs it hath been reputed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> and <hi>Lutheran Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Melanchthon,</hi> though in the beginning of the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they approved it, yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards deſerted it: This the later writings of <hi>Melanchthon</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently teſtifie of him. The ſame being witneſſed of the other by the <hi>Lutherans</hi> themſelves, who earneſtly contend rather for
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152178:57"/> their Maſters more full declaring of his judgement in this, then deſertion of the former opinion. <hi>Philip Melan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> believed this opinion of Predeſtination not much different from the <hi>Stoical Fate,</hi> as his papers teſtifie, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally his Epiſtle to <hi>Caſper Peuce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, [Lelius certifies the conteſts are grown ſo high at Geneva about the Stoical Fate, that one is impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned becauſe he differs from Zeno. O miſerable times! the doctrine of the Gospell obſcured with ſtrange and forraign diſputes!]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The diſſent of the <hi>Daniſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> in general is evident from the writings of <hi>Nicholas Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge</hi> in his Treatife of <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal grace,</hi> where he thus ſtates the <hi>Controverſie</hi> with his Adverſaries, [<hi>Whether the Elect believe, or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are elected?]</hi> Thoſe who aſſert the firſt, he judges them to agree with the doctrine of the <hi>Manichees</hi> and <hi>Stoicks;</hi> thoſe of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152178:57"/> the later perſwaſion, with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, Many in our owne Countrey do ſo ill reſent this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as they have openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd they neither can nor will have communion with our Church. Some that have joyned themſelves, yet with this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they could not cloſe with this opinion; and not a few (upon the ſcore of Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation onely) have fallen away from our Churches, who have been of the ſame minde with us; others threatning to leave us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they were ſatisfied; the <hi>Church</hi> was not of this judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Certainly, there is no doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal point, the <hi>Papiſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Lutherans</hi> do more ſharply oppoſe, and by whoſe means pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure greater envy to our <hi>Church,</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:152178:58"/> caſting an <hi>Odium</hi> upon all the <hi>Doctrines</hi> thereof, as if there were no blaſphemy againſt God ſo dreadful, either utterable or imaginable, which according to this opinion of our <hi>Teachers,</hi> might not upon good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence bee deduced from this Predeſtination.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, There was rarely ever any difficulty, or controverſie in theſe our Churches all along ſince the times of Reformation, which hath not had its riſe from this Doctrine, or been in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with it: For the truth of this, wee may recollect the conteſts at <hi>Leyden</hi> in the matter of <hi>Coolhaſius;</hi> thoſe at <hi>Gouda,</hi> in the buſineſs of <hi>Herman Herberts;</hi> thoſe at <hi>Horn</hi> about <hi>Cornelius Wigyer,</hi> and <hi>Medenblick</hi> in the cauſe of <hi>Taco Sibrand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was not the leaſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive inducing me to a diligent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimadvertency
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152178:58"/> of this point, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring that no damage ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue thereby unto our Churches; the Papacy hence geting ground, whoſe ruin (as of the Kingdome of Antichriſt) all pious Teachers ought to wiſh, ſtudiouſly ſeek, and as much as in them lies, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue: And this in brief, is that I have meditated upon this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Predeſtination, as it hath in all faithfulneſs been propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by mee from the Authours thereof, not affixing the leaſt ſyllable to them which I cannot clearly prove from their own wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</p>
               <p>Others of our Teachers do hold forth the Doctrine of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with ſome diffrence from the former, and that two ſeveral wayes, which I will briefly run through.</p>
               <p>The Judgement of ſome of them is this.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:152178:59"/>
               <p>Firſt, That God hath purpoſed in himſelf by an Eternal and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable Decree, out of the lump of mankinde, to make the leſſer part (for his good pleaſure) par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of grace and glory, to the praiſe of his renowned Mercy; but by his preterition, to leave the greater part in the ſtate of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, impotent to ſupernatural things, and not communicate to them that ſaving and ſpiritual grace, by which their nature yet whole and integrate might be eſtabliſh'd; or corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved, reſtored to the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his Liberty; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward being made peccant and culpable, to puniſh them with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal death, for the illuſtration of his Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Predeſtination (which word with theſe men is taken in the ſtrict ſenſe for Election, and oppoſed to Reprobation) is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable <hi>in reſpect of the end and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152178:59"/> the means leading thereunto.</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>end,</hi> which is ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a <hi>manifeſto</hi> of his glorious grace, Man's conſider'd abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and indifferently in his own nature in reference to the <hi>means;</hi> he is looked upon as of himſelf, and in himſelf periſhing, and as guilty in <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, In the Decree, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the end, theſe gradations are obſervable; <hi>Gods preſcience</hi> by which he foreknew the predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, then <hi>his prefinition,</hi> by which he preordain'd the ſalvation of thoſe whom he foreknew: Firſt; By electing them from eternity; then by preparing grace for them in this life, and glory in the life to come.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Means appertaining to the execution of this Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>are to be Chriſt himſelf;</hi> then <hi>efficacious calling to faith in him;</hi> whence ariſeth <hi>Justification,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152178:60"/> and then the gift of perſeverance</hi> to the end.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Reprobation, as we are capable of underſtanding it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of two acts, <hi>Preterition,</hi> and <hi>Predamnation;</hi> the firſt anteceda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous to all things &amp; cauſes which are either in them, or exiſt by them; (<hi>i. e.</hi>) beholding man abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely and indifferently under no conſideration of ſin.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, To execute this act of <hi>Preterition,</hi> two means to be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, <hi>Dereliction</hi> in the ſtate of Nature, uncapable of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural performances, and <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication</hi> of grace, whereby their nature uncorrupted might be confirm'd, or depraved might be reſtored.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>Predamnation</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to precede all things; yet not without the <hi>preſcience</hi> of the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of damnation; God in his
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152178:60"/> foreknowledge beholding man as an offender, and guilty of death in <hi>Adam,</hi> therefore liable to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh out of the neceſſity impoſed upon him by Divine Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, The means ordained to put into execution this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damnation. 1. <hi>Juſt deſertion,</hi> and that's either of <hi>Exploration,</hi> wherein God conferres not his grace; or of <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> when God deprives man of all his <hi>ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiferous gifts,</hi> and delivers him up into the power of Satan. 2. Means <hi>hardening,</hi> and thoſe things that accompany it, to the real damnation of the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
               <p>Others declare their Opinion thus:<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, That God willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree from eternity the Election of particular perſons, &amp; Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others, looked upon man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152178:61"/> not onely as <hi>made,</hi> but as <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> and <hi>corrupted,</hi> and therefore guilty of Malediction, from which he determined freely by his grace to ſave ſome for a declarative of his Mercy, and leave others under the curſe in juſt Judgement, for a <hi>manifesto</hi> of his Juſtice; and this without any conſideration had of Repentance and Faith in the one, or Infidelity and Impenitence in the other.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The ſpecial means<note place="margin">See the ſtating of the firſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion.</note> particularly belonging to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of this Decree of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reprobation, <hi>are to be the ſame</hi> with thoſe laid down in the ſtating of the firſt Opinion, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepting thoſe in common, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining jointly to both; for the judgement of theſe men we now repreſent, makes not the fall of man as a <hi>means preordain'd</hi> to the accompliſhment of the preceding Decree of Predeſtination, but onely as a <hi>proaereſis,</hi> or an occaſion
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152178:61"/> adminiſtred for the framing hereof.</p>
               <p>Both of theſe Opinions, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Arminius</hi> examines theſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</note> to their outward ſhape, do in this only differ from the firſt, that they neither place Creation nor the fall as a middle cauſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed of God to execute this preceding Decree of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though the two later them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves agree not concerning the Fall. The firſt of them propounds <hi>Election</hi> in reſpect of the end, and <hi>preterition</hi> the firſt part of <hi>Reprobation,</hi> as preceding the fall, the ſecond, as both of them ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent thereunto. Amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſons inducing theſe men to deliver the Doctrine of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination this way, without kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the high Road with their Predeceſſors, this was not the meaneſt, their willingneſs to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, leſt God with the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability ſhould be concluded <hi>the Author of ſin</hi> from this their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152178:62"/> as ſome of them have jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it concludable from the firſt. But really, if with diligent inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction we well examine theſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of a later <note n="*" place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Edition, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the Judgements of the ſame Authors in other points of <hi>Religion,</hi> we ſhall find the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> not poſſibly otherwayes conſiderable, (according to the Tenents of theſe men) then as a neceſſary executive means of the preceding Decree of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and this the purport of the two reaſons comprehended in the ſecond Opinion apparently evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. The firſt is, Gods deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination by the Decree of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, to deny unto man that grace neceſſary to the antidoting his nature againſt the poyſon of ſin; (<hi>i. e.</hi>) decreed not to confer that grace which was neceſſary to avoid obliquity; ſo that mans <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> being under a Law, becomes inevitable, and his fall a means appointed to bring in to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152178:62"/> act the Decree of Reprobation. The ſecond is, their bicotomy of Reprobation into <hi>Preterition</hi> and <hi>Predamnation,</hi> which according to the tenor of this Decree are cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled together by a neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion one with another, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually extenſive; for all they that were <hi>paſſed</hi> by of God in the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of grace, are alſo damned, and no others; whence we gather, <hi>Sin is a neceſſary reſult of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Reprobation;</hi> otherwayes there were a poſſibility of not ſinning left unto perſons under this <hi>Preterition,</hi> and ſo of not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, (ſin being the only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing cauſe of damnation) and ſo ſome thus paſſed by of God, neither ſaved nor condemned, which is a great abſurdity. This Opinion we ſee is obnoxious to the ſame inconvenience with the firſt; and whileſt it endeavours to avoid it, it falls into an open and abſurd contradiction of it ſelf,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152178:63"/> according to this; <hi>Prima ubi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſu ſimilis ſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Opinion eſcapes this <hi>Rock</hi> better then the other, had<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Permiſſio peccati eſt privatio auxilii Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vini, quo poſito, pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediretur; VVhitaker</hi> quoted by <hi>Maccovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Coll. Theol.</hi>
                  </note> not the Patrons thereof deliver'd ſome thing for the declaration of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> and <hi>Providence,</hi> from whence the neceſſity of the Fall may be inferred, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have any other riſe then Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatory ordination. Their deſcription of divine permiſsion of ſin is very pertinent; [<hi>Permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is the ſubſtraction of Divine grace, whereby God, (executing the decrees of his will by rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi>)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Substracto auxilio Dei homo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatibus ad ſtandum bene ut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> non potuit.</hi> Paraeus, cap. 4. p. 46. lib. De Gratia primi hom.</note> 
                  <hi>either doth not reveal his will to the creature, whereby he would have it effected; or doth not incline its will in that act in obedience to his own.</hi>] To which they adde, <hi>If it be ſo, the creature ſins neceſſarily, yet voluntarily and freely.</hi> If any reply, This deſcription is not qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant to Gods permiſsion of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> ſin, we cloſe with him; yet
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152178:63"/> nevertheleſs, hence it follows, That all other ſins are done una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably. Again, It's reducible hither what ſome of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with that eagerneſs for, <hi>viz.</hi> That the manifeſtation of glory divine, which needs muſt be illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, is placed in the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Mercy and Juſtice punitive, which cannot be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but by the entrance of ſin and miſery by it, at leaſt to the loweſt deſert thereof into the world; ſuch a declarative of Gods glory introducing a neceſsity of ſinning; And the Apoſtacie of <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unavoidable, therefore it (together with Creation) are means ſubſervient to the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Decree; mans revolt could not neceſſarily enſue upon his Creation, unleſs by vertue of this predeſtinatory Decree, which cannot hold any middle place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, but is ſet over them precedaneous to them both, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bordinating Creation to Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152178:64"/> and both to the execution of one and the ſame decree, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſin, and <hi>Mercy</hi> in the remiſſion thereof: Otherwiſe the neceſſary ſequel of Creation had not been intended by God in it, which is impoſſible. But grant the neceſſity of the fall could not be concluded from the premiſes of either theſe two laſt Opinions, yet all the forementioned Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments levell'd againſt the firſt, with a little diverſification, are prevalent againſt theſe; as would plainly appear upon a debate of them.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have declared the Opinions of others in the point of Predeſtination, ſo much incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in our <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> of Leyden, together with my own reaſons inducing me to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowance of them: I come in the laſt place to offer my own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning it, and as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152178:64"/> moſt conformable to the <hi>Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt and abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Arminius</hi> his own Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the point in hand.</note> of God concerning the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ſinful Man, is that whereby he decreed to appoint <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Mediator, Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Saviour, Priest</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> who ſhould aboliſh ſinne by his death, recover (by his obedience) loſt righteouſneſs, and by his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue communicate the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond preciſe and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute decree of God, is that whereby he determined to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive into favour repentant and believing perſons, and thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering to the end, to ſave in Chriſt, for Chriſt, and by Chriſt; the impenitent and unbelievers to leave in ſin under wrath, and deſtroy as aliens from Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third decree, is that whereby he ordained (to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152178:65"/> ſufficiently and efficaciouſly) <hi>means</hi> neceſſary to faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and this adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be framed according to his <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> whereby he knowes what beſt becomes his mercy and ſeverity, and according to his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> by which he is prepared to follow the preſcript of his Wiſdome, and put the ſame into execution.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hence follows the fourth, whereby he decreed the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and condemnation of ſome ſingular and certain perſons; and this Divine Ordination leans upon his <hi>Preſciency,</hi> whereby hee knew from eternity, who (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the vouchſafement of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneous means to faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion by his preventing grace) were to believe, and by his ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent perſevere, &amp; who were not to believe nor perſevere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:152178:65"/>
               <head>This Predeſtination thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, is,</head>
               <p n="1">1. The Foundation of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, Salvation,</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Materials</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, yea the very Goſpel it ſelf; and as to the two firſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles thereof, neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved unto ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither hath it had need to be examined or diſcuſs'd in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>General</hi> or <hi>Particular Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils,</hi> being clearly and expreſly <hi>totidem verbis</hi> contained in the Scriptures, nor ever contradicted by any Orthodox Divine.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Alwayes acknowledged and held forth by all ſound Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It accords with the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of all Confeſſions ſet forth by the <hi>Proteſtant Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. It agrees very fitly with the <hi>Belg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ck Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme;</hi> and if the words in the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152178:66"/> 16. <hi>Art. [Some and others</hi>] be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by beleevers and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, my judgement is dilucidly comprehended in it, which moved me (being to diſpute publikely in the Colledge) to order the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions<note place="margin">In Collegio publico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privato Academiae</note> to be ſtated in the words of the <hi>Confeſſion.</hi> It agrees with the Catechiſm, <hi>Queſt.</hi> 20. 54.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It very well ſutes the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, viz.</hi> his <hi>wiſdome, goodneſs, and righteouſneſs,</hi> is the principal matter and cleareſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It's at very good agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the <hi>Nature of Man,</hi> whether conſidered in the ſtate of Innocency, Apoſtacy, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration.</p>
               <p n="9">9. It holds good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with the <hi>Act of Creati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> confirming it to be the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of good, according to the intent of God, and the event of the thing; that it had its riſe from <hi>Divine goodneſs,</hi> its continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and preſervation from <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152178:66"/> Love,</hi> and that it is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and proper work of God, wherein he pleaſed himſelf, and procured all things which were neceſſary, <hi>ad non peccandum,</hi> to a not ſinning.</p>
               <p n="10">10. It conſents with the <hi>Nature of eternal life,</hi> and thoſe titles wherewith it is dignified in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p n="11">11. With the <hi>Property of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death,</hi> and thoſe names put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="12">12. It makes ſinne to be truly diſobedience, and the meritorious cauſe of condemnation, and ſo concords with Apoſtacy and Tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p n="13">13. It harmonizeth with the <hi>Nature of Grace,</hi> by aſcribing all things competible thereunto, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling it to his juſtice, and the nature and liberty of Mans will.</p>
               <p n="14">14. It's a moſt advantagious declarative of the glory of <hi>Gods Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> repreſenting
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152178:67"/> him the cauſe of all good, and our ſalvation; and Man the cauſe of fin, and his own ruin.</p>
               <p n="15">15. It contributes to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> appointing him the foundation of Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the procuring and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatory cauſe of ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="16">16. It greatly promotes the ſalvation of men, being the power and means unto everlaſting life, procreating in them ſorrow for <hi>ſin, a ſollicitous care of converſion, faith in Chriſt, ſtudy of good works, zeal in prayer, cauſing us to work out our ſalvation with fear and trembling,</hi> and as far as is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, hinders deſperation.</p>
               <p n="17">17. It confirms and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that <hi>Order and Method</hi> the Preaching of the Goſpel requires; Firſt, exacting <hi>Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> then promiſing <hi>Remiſſion of Sin,</hi> the <hi>grace of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>eternal life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. It ſtrengthens the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Goſpel, and renders
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152178:67"/> it fruitful in the promulgation thereof, adminiſtry of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Publike Prayers.</p>
               <p n="19">19. It is the foundation of Chriſtianity, in that in it the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Love of God</hi> are haply joyned together, and at good agreement one with another, namely, his <hi>Love of Righteouſneſs</hi> with his <hi>love of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, This doctrine hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been allowed of by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of Chriſtians, and to this day ſtands approved by them; neither can it adminiſter an occaſion of its abhorrency, or ground of contention in the Chriſtian Church: Its much to be wiſhed, that men would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no further in this matter, neither be inquiſitive into the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable <hi>judgements of God</hi> any more then as revealed in the Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:152178:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>And this is that (moſt Noble and Potent States) I have to declare to your Highneſs's concerning this Doctrine ſo much ventilated in the Church of Chriſt: And if I ſhould not be burdenſome, I have other things to offer to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's conducing to the declaration of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udgement, and leading to the ſelf-ſame end, for which I am commanded hither by your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's:</hi> The Providence of God; <hi>the</hi> Free-will of Man; Perſeverance of Saints; Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Salvation, <hi>are points of ſo great affinity with this Doctrine of Predeſtination, and have ſo much dependance upon it, that with your good leave I ſhall deliver my ſelf upon them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Providence of</hi> GOD, I judge to be that careful, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual, and ever-preſent eye of God, by which the care of the whole <hi>Univerſe,</hi> and all particular
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152178:68"/> Creatures (not one exempted) is upon him, to the conſervation and government of them in their eſſence, qualities, actions, and paſſions, as it beſt becomes him and ſutes them, to the glory of his Name, and ſalvation of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers. Herein I ſubſtract no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from <hi>Divine Providence</hi> competible to it; but yeeld it the conſervation, regulation, gubernation, and direction of all things, even to the abolition of Chance and Fortune; yea, I ſubject to the great Providence the <hi>Will of Man, and the very acts of the rational creature,</hi> ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is done without its will, though contrary thereunto: This difference betwixt good and bad actions onely obſerved; in that we affirm <hi>God both to will, and do good acts,</hi> but freely to permit the bad, being willing to concede the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution of all acts excogitable concerning evil to the providence of God, ſo wee take heed leſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152178:69"/> thence God be determin'd <hi>The Author of Sin,</hi> which I evidently enough teſtified in a Diſpute once and again under me at <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> concerning the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and efficacious Providence of God in evill; in which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to aſcribe unto Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence all thoſe acts concerning ſin attributed to God in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, making ſuch progreſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that occaſion was taken by ſome of impeaching me with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king GOD <hi>the Author of Sin,</hi> which was often produced againſt me at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> according to their ſuggeſtion from thoſe <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> but how juſtly, it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently manifeſt from my anſwer to the one and thirty <hi>Articles</hi> (mentioned above) falſly impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon me, this being one of them.</p>
               <p>Touching <hi>mans will,</hi> I am of that opinion that he was in dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with knowledg, holineſs and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152178:69"/> other ablities by his Creation, whereby he was able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, eſtimate, conſider, will and performe true good; even as far as the commandment obliged him; yet not this without the auxiliaries of <hi>Divine grace:</hi> In the ſtate of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>ſin,</hi> he is diſabled of himſelfe and by himſelf to think, will, or do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing truly good, and ſtands in need of the renovating and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating power of God in Chriſt by his Spirit in his <hi>intellect affections, will</hi> and all other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, to impower him hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; but, participating hereof as freed from ſin, he is able to think will and do good, yet ſtill as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Supplies of the <hi>grace of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>grace of God</hi> I believe it to be that gratuitous and undeſerved <hi>aſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> whereby God is well affected towards a miſerable ſinner; by which, firſt he gave his <hi>Son, that whoſoever
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152178:70"/> believe's in him might have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life; and then in and for Chriſt juſtifies him, and adopts him into the right of his ſons unto Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. It is the infuſion of Spiritual gifts into the underſtanding, will, and affections of man, appertaining to his regeneration and renovation, viz. <hi>Faith, hope, Charity</hi> &amp;c. without which gratious donatives, man is not meet to think, will or do any thing that good is.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Grace</hi> is that continued <hi>aſſiſtance,</hi> that non-intermiſſive helpe of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> by which the <hi>Spirit</hi> doth inſtantly perſwade &amp; excite man, (before Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate) unto goodneſſe, infuſing Salutiferous cogitations, inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him with holy deſiers, to the willing of good Actually; yea alſo by this he ſo wills and works together with man, that what man will's, he might accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152178:70"/> And thus I atribute to <hi>Grace</hi> the <hi>begining, continuance, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of all good,</hi> ſo far as that man now regenerate, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this preventing, exciting, Subſequent, and Cooperating Grace, is in capable to think, will, or do any good, or reſiſt any noxious temptation. Hence it's apparently manifeſt, I am no way injurious to the <hi>grace of God,</hi> by aſcribing too much to the <hi>free will of man,</hi> as ſome aſperſe me. The hinge upon which al the Controvercy is turned, is this; whether the grace of God be an irreſiſtible force: actions and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations as aſcribable to grace, are not here diſputed, none more ready then my ſelfe to confeſſe and inculcate them all; the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the operation onely is that in debate, wherein I believe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, <hi>that many reſiſt the HolyGhoſt, and repell Grace offered them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:152178:71"/>
               <p>As to the perſeverance of Saints my judgement is this, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons engrafted into Chriſt by true Faith, and participating of his quickning ſpirit, have ſtrength ſufficient to encounter Satan, Sin, the World, and their own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, <hi>and by the ſame aſſiſting grace to carry away the Victory;</hi> Chriſt himſelf ſtanding by them in their aſſaults by his ſpirit, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his favourable hand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them (<hi>ſo they be found in a fighting poſture; implore his aid, and not be awanting to themſelves</hi>) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them from falling; ſo that neither the fraud or violence of Satan ſhall be able to ſeduce or pluck them out of his hands. But whether theſe very perſons by negligence <hi>may not deſert the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their exiſtency in Chriſt, embrace again this preſent world, fall from the ſound Doctrine once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd to them, loſe a good conſcience, make void the grace of God,</hi> would be diligently inquired into out of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152178:71"/> the Scriptures, and very uſeful and neceſſary to be debated in our firſt convention; yet I profeſs ingenuouſly, It was never taught by me that the true Believer <hi>might totally or finally fall away from the faith, and ſo periſh;</hi> though I cannot diſſemble, there are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture which ſeem to countenance the ſame, to which I could never meet with any ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory anſwer, although on the other part there are ſome places alledged not unworthy of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
               <p>Concerning aſſurance of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I judge him who believes in Jeſus Chriſt, as well by the act of the holy ſpirit inwardly moving, and the Fruits of Faith, as by his own conſcience, with the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the ſpirit witneſſing with it, <hi>may have a certain perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and indeed be aſſured, if his heart condemn him not that he is the ſon of God, and ſtands in the love of Chriſt;</hi> yea more, may depart
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152178:72"/> this life with an unſhaken confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the grace of God, and mercy in Chriſt Jeſus, and appear before that Tribunal of grace de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void of all anxious fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſolicitude; yet ought he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to pray, <hi>Lord, enter not into judgement with me;</hi> but in as much as God is greater then our hearts, and knoweth all things, and man not his own Judge; for though he know nothing by himſelf, yet is he not thereby juſtified, it is God that judgeth him: I dare not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual this certainty with that wherewith we know <hi>there is a God,</hi> and that <hi>Christ is the Saviour of the world;</hi> but the extent of this may be further treated of in our Convention.</p>
               <p>Beſides all theſe, there hath been much diſcourſe abroad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>perfection of Believers and regenerate perſons in this life;</hi> wherein I have been traduced as heterodox, and as almoſt of the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152178:72"/> Pelagian Opinion in this point, <hi>viz.</hi> That the regenerate in this life <hi>may perfectly keep the Law of God.</hi> To which I anſwer, That if I ſhould thus judge, yet ſhould I not Pelagianize either in whole, or in part, if ſo be I added this, they were able to do <hi>by the grace of Chriſt, and not without it;</hi> yet that there could be a plenary ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of <hi>the precepts of Chriſt by a renewed perſon in this life,</hi> I never affirm'd, neither ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but left it alwaies dubious, contenting my ſelf with that of <hi>Auſtine,</hi> whoſe words I often quoted in the Univerſity, having nothing to adde of my own; they were theſe: <hi>There are four queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auſtine</hi>'s Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
                  <hi>obſervable in the buſineſs in hand; 1. Whether there was ever any man without Sin who from the beginning to the end of his life never tranſgreſſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>Whether there ever hath been, now is, or ever can be any ſuch
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152178:73"/> perſon that ſinneth not,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>who hath reached that perfection here that he tranſgreſſeth not, but fulfils the Law of the perfect God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. <hi>Whether there be a poſſibility in this life for a man to be without Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. <hi>If't be poſsible, why there was never any ſuch perſon found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the firſt the Father anſwers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>That there was never any ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon found beſides the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the ſecond, <hi>He thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any man attained perfection in this life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the third, <hi>He judged it poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by the grace of God and mans free-will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the fourth, <hi>Man doth not that which is poſsible by the grace of Chriſt, either becauſe he is ignorant what good is, or places no complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or delight in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:152178:73"/>
               <p>Hence its apparently manifeſt, <hi>Austine</hi> (the ſharpeſt adverſary the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Doctrine ever had) was of this Judgement, That it <hi>was poſsible by the grace of Chriſt in this life to be without ſin:</hi> Yea, he further addes, Let <hi>Pelagius</hi> confeſs mans poſsibility of being without ſin to be only <hi>by the grace of Chriſt,</hi> and we are agreed; but the <hi>Pelag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an</hi> Tenent appeared to this Father as if man by his <hi>own ſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gth</hi> (though with greater facility <hi>by the grace of Chriſt</hi>) had been able to keep the whole Law: How far I diſſent from this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I have enter'd above, and now teſtifie mine account of it as Heretical diametrically oppoſite to the words of Chriſts, <hi>Without me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e can do nothing,</hi> and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly<note place="margin">John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. 9</note> deſtructive to the glory of God.</p>
               <p>My judgement thus ſtated, I cannot ſee any thing comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein, for which any man
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152178:74"/> ſhould juſtly fear <hi>to appear toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with it in the preſence of God,</hi> or ſuſpect any grievous evil to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe;<note place="margin">He refers to Mr. <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to the States, p. 1.</note> yet being ſenſible of thoſe daylie Aſperſions more and more caſt upon me, as if I ſhould carry in my boſome ſome pernicious Heretical opinions, I am not able to divine what the matter is, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they pretend ſomething amiſs in my Judgement <hi>concerning the divinity of the Son of God, and mans juſtificat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on before him;</hi> for as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, touching both theſe heads much ſpeech was had after the laſt Act before the Supreme Court, and many things given out upon it, for which I think my ſelf engaged to declare to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the carriage of the whole buſineſs.</p>
               <p>That which relates <hi>to the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Son of God, and the word</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of which a Diſpute was once had in our Univerſity; I cannot enough wonder, what
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152178:74"/> brought me into ſuſpition with ſome men, their jealouſly not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grounded upon the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, indeed as much remote from reaſon and truth, as what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is diſperſed to the prejudice of my Repute herein, may be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly termed notoriouſly ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. At a diſpute one Afternoon in <hi>Leyden,</hi> the queſtion concern'd the Divinity of Chriſt; the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent objected the Son of God was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and therefore had his eſſence of himſelf, and not of his Father. The Reſpondent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken two waies, and either ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him who was <hi>truly God, or him who was God of himſelf;</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the firſt acception it was well and truly attributable to the Son of God; according to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was not. The Student ſtill urging his Argument, vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contended, that this was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petible to him according to the ſecond ſignification, and the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152178:75"/> of the Father could not be ſaid, but improperly, to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the Son and Holy Ghoſt, and that in right and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety it was common to them all; and this he managed with the greater confidence, having Mr. <hi>Trelcatius Junior</hi> of bleſſed memory for him, as appears by ſome paſſages in his Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>places to this purpoſe. To which I then anſwered, That this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was oppugnant to the Word of God, and all the antient <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Churhes, who alwaies taught, That the Son <hi>had his Deity by eternal generation from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and that it unavoidably drew along with it two repugnant Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, <hi>Tritheiſm,</hi> and <hi>Sabellianiſm; (i. e.</hi>) hence would inevitably fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a Trinity of Gods, who ſhould together collaterally have divine Eſſence, without the one having it from another, being only perſonally diſtinct; when for the defence of the unity of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152178:75"/> Eſſence in the trinity of perſons, this only Fundamental hath been adhibited, <hi>the original Progreſs of one perſon from another,</hi> namely that of the Son from the Father. Hence would alſo follow, the confounding of the Father with the Son, inferring only a nominal difference betwixt them, which was the Opinion of <hi>Sabellius.</hi> It's proper to the Father to have <hi>his Deity of himſelf,</hi> or to ſpeak more rightly, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f none,</hi> if in this ſenſe the Son were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, God of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he ſhould be the Father.</p>
               <p>This Diſpute went every where abroad, and reached <hi>Amſterdam</hi> it ſelf, where I was enquired of by a Miniſter now fallen aſleep in the Lord, how the caſe ſtood, who received a full account of me, with my deſires that he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form <hi>Trel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atius</hi> of pious memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, admoniſh him to rectifie his Judgement, and correct thoſe impertinent words in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-places,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152178:76"/> which after a ſort he took upon him to do. Herein I was far from being liable to any blame, having defended the truth and the Judgement of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and Orthodox Church; but rather <hi>Trelcatius,</hi> who had uſurp'd a form of ſpeaking dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to the truth of the thing. This is my infelicity, or the zeal of ſome men, the leaſt variance ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to have all the fault caſt upon me, as if 'twere more impoſſible for me to be found in the Faith then any other man, though herein M. <hi>Gomar</hi> aſſented, who in a diſpute concerning the Trinity, not long after the publication of thoſe forementioned Common-places, did in his <hi>Theſes</hi> three ſeveral times contradict Mr. <hi>Trelcatius,</hi> which I ſhewed the <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Miniſter, who confeſſed the ſame; yet notwithſtanding all this, none endeavour'd my vindication from this <hi>obloquie,</hi> as ſome did the excuſal of Mr. <hi>Trelcatius,</hi> by all
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152178:76"/> can did Interpretation, which yet could not ſtand in any conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with the words: So much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor and zeal could do.</p>
               <p>Their tender Interpretation was this, The Son of God may be ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or ſaid to have his Divinity of himſelf, <hi>quà Deus,</hi> as he is God; though from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>quà Filius,</hi> as he is a Son. It's only for enlargement that God or Eſſence ought to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>abſolutely</hi> and <hi>relatively;</hi> in the firſt acception the Son to have Eſſence Divine of himſelf; in the other from his Father. Theſe are new Modes of ſpeaking, novel o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and inconſiſtent; for the Son, both as God, and as Son, hath his deity from his Father; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of God only, doth not expreſs his being from the Father, as the word Son doth. The Eſſence of God is not any way conſiderable, wherein it can be ſaid not to be communicated
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152178:77"/> to the Son from the Father; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any diverſe reſpect can the ſame Eſſence both be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated &amp; not communicated to him; being Contradictories they cannot be reconciled in any double conſideration: If it be relatively communicated to him, he cannot have it abſolutely of himſelf. I ſhall be peradventure demanded, Whether to be God, and the Son of God, be not two diſtinct things, which is confeſſed, but when by a further proceſs it's affirm'd that as to be the Son of God, imports his having an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from the Father; ſo to be God, implies the having it from himſelf, or from none: It's denied with a further aſſervation, That it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. an Error, not only in Divinity, but natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy alſo. To be a Son<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to be God, are at no repugnancy one with another; but to have an Eſſence from the Father, and yet withal to have it from none, are
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152178:77"/> contradictories, and mutually deſtroy one another.</p>
               <p>To bring this Fallacy to the light, we muſt obſerve the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollencie of theſe ſix propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, placed parallel-wiſe.</p>
               <p>God is eternal, having Divine Eſſence from Eternity.</p>
               <p>The Father is from none, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Divine Eſſence from none.</p>
               <p>The Son is of the Father, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Divine Eſſence from the Father.</p>
               <p>The word God imports the having true Divine Eſſence. The term Son implies the having the ſame from the Father, whence properly he is called both God, and the Son of God; but as he cannot be called Father, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he be ſaid to have eſſence of himſelf, or from no other; yet what endeavours are made to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152178:78"/> excuſe theſe things, by telling us, that when the Son of God, as God, is ſaid to have Eſſence of himſelf, nothing elſe is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, but that Eſſence Divine proceeds not from any. But if they are pleaſed to do thus, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be ſo depravedly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, which an excuſe may not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize. Although God and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence Differ not <note n="*" place="margin">Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet whatever is predicable of the later, may not be predicated of the firſt, becauſe diſtinguiſhable after our manner of conception, to which all forms of ſpeaking ought to be exacted; therefore made uſe of that by them we may have a right perceptive of things. Hence it appears we ſpeak right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in ſaying <hi>Gods Eſſence is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable;</hi> but falſly, <hi>that God may be communicated;</hi> he that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the difference 'twixt the <hi>Abſtract</hi> and the <hi>Concrete,</hi> ſo much controverted 'twixt the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and us muſt eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152178:78"/> how many abſurdities would follow, if ſuch Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as theſe were once permitted in the Church of God: It admits of no excuſe <hi>that the Son of God ſhould be</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, neither is it proper to ſay that <hi>the Eſsence of God is common to the three perſons,</hi> when it's ſaid to be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one from another. From what I ſay it's openly manifeſt how much we can tolerate in him whom we ſuſpect not of Hereſie, and on the contrary how greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſnatch up any thing to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den him whom we have in ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the firſt is conſpicuous; for the later, this example is the leaſt.</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>man's justification before God,</hi> I am not conſcious to my ſelf of teaching or thinking any thing which is not the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſenſe of the reform'd and Proteſtant Churches, and at very good accord with their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments herein.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:152178:79"/>
               <p>Some controverſie of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture indeed there was afoot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Piſcator</hi> the <hi>Naſſovian</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity, and the French Churches, ſtated thus; <hi>Whether the obedience and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and in which they are righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before God, were only the paſsive obedience of Chriſt, according to the judgement of</hi> Piſcator; <hi>or both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and paſsive, which in his whole life he yeelded to the Law of God, and that holineſs wherein hee was conceived, as the</hi> Gallick Churches <hi>believed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For my part, I never durſt ſink into this queſtion, or aſſume the examination thereof, being ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the Profeſſors of the ſame Religion may diſſent from one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother herein, ſalving the unity of Faith and Chriſtian Peace; the Adverſaries one to another ſeeming to be of the ſame minde in mutual toleration and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152178:79"/> forbearance, although in our Countrey ſome be of another judgement.</p>
               <p>A Queſtion is mov'd from the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Rom. 4. [Faith was accounted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi>] whether it be underſtood properly, ſo that faith as an act done according to the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Precept, be imputed before God to or for righteouſneſs, and that by grace, in as much as it is not the righteouſneſs of the Law; or whether it be to be underſtood figuratively, and improperly, that the righteouſneſs of Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by Faith, be imputed to us for righteouſneſs; or thus, whether Righteouſneſs (into, or for which faith is imputed) bee the inſtrumental work thereof, as ſome aſſert. I have followed the firſt opinion, in the <hi>Theſes</hi> of Juſtification diſputed under<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> me, <hi>Non praecisè</hi> not rigidly, yet <hi>ſimpli itèr,</hi> plainly, as elſewhere
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152178:80"/> in a certain Epiſtle. For this I am judged unſound in the doctrine of mans Juſtification; but this wil be more clearly manifeſt in a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al conference in its due ſeaſon: For the preſent briefly thus: <hi>I believe the juſtification of ſinners by the ſole obedience of Chriſt, and that his Righteouſneſs is the onely merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cauſe for which the condonation of ſin is granted to believers, and reputed as juſt as if they had fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Law perfectly; but inaſmuch as God imputes this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to believers only, I judg in this ſenſe it may be well and properly ſaid, that faith is imputed for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs by grace to him that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, God having ſet forth his Son</hi> Tribunal Gratiae, <hi>a Mercy-ſeat, or propitiation by faith in his blood.</hi> But however my judgement is the ſame with <hi>Calvins,</hi> (whom none of us reprehends as unſold in this point) and am ready to ſubſcribe to what he layes down in the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152178:80"/> third booke of his Inſtitutions concerning it.</p>
               <p>And theſe are the chief Articles, moſt noble and potent States, at the command of theſe Seſſions I judged neceſsary to declare my ſenſe of.</p>
               <p>I have made ſome annotations upon the Confeſſion of the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Churches and Heydelberge Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm;</hi> but of theſe a debate will be moſt ſeaſonable in our Synod, which with your conſent and evocation we hope for by the firſt opportunity; only give me leave to add a word or two concerning a certaine Claufe, under which the Noble and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent States Generall conſented to a <hi>Nationall Synod</hi> in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; which was this, that in it the Confeſſion and Catechiſm of the <hi>Belgick Churches</hi> ſhould be ſubjected to Examination. This hath diſpleaſed many, who judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152178:81"/> it not onely unneceſſary, but very unmeet to be done; and who ſhould procure this from the Lords the States Generall, but a perſon of quality and my ſelfe? But neither of theſe upon any ground; for the later, we were ſo far from being the authors of it, that eleven or twelve years ago at the great importunity of the Churches for a <hi>Nationall Synod,</hi> the States of South-Holland and Weſtfrieſland could not judg it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe requiſite to yeeld there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by their decree, then that in it the <hi>Confeſſion of the Belgick Churches ſhould be brought under Examination;</hi> we not promoting any ſuch thing at that time either by advice or endeavour; yet real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if we had, we had done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but our duty, and what was agreeable both to Equity and Reaſon, and the neceſſity of our preſent Eſtate.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:152178:81"/>
               <p>Firſt, that it might appeare to all the world we bear that honour to the word of God alone (as becomes us) that it onely is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to be without, nay above all diſpute, beyond al exception, and worthy of all acceptation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, theſe book's being the writings of men Errour may be contain'd in them, whence it behoves us to be inquiſitive, (yet lawfully in a Nationall Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod) whether there be any thing that ſtands need of Correction and emendation in them.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Whether they have an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of parts with the word of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>i. e.</hi> An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout.</note> God, as well according to the words themſelves and manner of ſpeaking, as the genuine ſenſe thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether or no whatſoever is Comprehended in them, be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be believed unto ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152178:82"/> ſo conſequently, ſaving health aſcribed to thoſe things to which it is not Competible.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether the Confeſſion doth not containe and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend too many things as neceſſary to be believed unto ſalvation, and that ſaving health according to that rule be refuſed to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to what it appertaines.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether the words and form's of ſpeaking made uſe of in them, are not of ambiguous accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, adminiſtring an occaſion of contention; for Example, 14. <hi>Art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Confeſ.</hi> you have this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>Nothing is done without Gods ordination;</hi> if by <hi>ordination</hi> be meant <hi>Gods appointing</hi> that ſomething be done, the Propoſition is falſe, in that it follows, that God is the <hi>Author of ſin;</hi> but if the import of it be, his <hi>Ordination to a good end,</hi> its rightly underſtood.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:152178:82"/>5. Whether there may not be found things repugnant one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. <hi>Ex. Gr.</hi> A perſon much honoured in the Church, writes to <hi>Piſcator;</hi> the <hi>Naſſovian</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor wiſhes him to adhere to the Heydelberge Catechiſm; in his Doctrine of Juſtification cites to this purpoſe three places, which he thought at variance with the judgement of <hi>Piſcator.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor returns, For his part he did ſtedfaſtly abide in the ſenſe of the Catechiſm, alledgeth for his proof eleven or twelve places thence. Now I ſolemnly profeſs, I ſee not how theſe places admit of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether all things in theſe writings be digeſted in that right order and method the Scripture requires them to be.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether all things be moſt aptly conſtituted for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of peace and unity with all Reformed Churches.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:152178:83"/>
               <p>3 Reaſon. The end of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Synod, is, diligently to conſult the right ordering the affairs of the Church, to which chiefly belongs a Doctrinal Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, as well that which by Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous conſent is admitted of, as what ſome Teachers earneſtly contend for.</p>
               <p>4. Reaſon Such an Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as this will not only procure authority to theſe writings, when after a Mature and rigid Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny they ſhall be found concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the Word of God, or more and more conform'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; but alſo raiſe the credit of the Miniſters in the minds of men, when they perceive the truth reveald in the Book of God to be ſo deare, and of that great account with them, that they will ſpare no pains to ſet their Doctrine in a greater Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity thereunto.</p>
               <p>5 Reaſon. Why if at any time, now eſpecially we Judge
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152178:83"/> ſuch a thing neceſſary, becauſe there are many Miniſters having ſome Meditations by them upon ſeveral things contained in the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> which they ſecretly reſerve, not revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to any, hoping to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate them in a <hi>National Synod;</hi> this being promiſed them, ſome ſuffer themſelves to be perſwaded not to permit their thoughts herein to ſee the light.</p>
               <p>Further; The end of a <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Synod</hi> ſhould be this, That it may pleaſe the Noble and Potent Lords and States to eſtabliſh ſome Eccleſiaſtick Sanctions by publick authority, according to which every one ought to frame himſelf in the Church of God. That this may be obtained from your moſt illuſtrious Highneſſes, and others able to execute the ſame with a good Conſcience, its neceſſary <hi>They underſtand the Doctrine comprehended in the forme of unity to be Conſentaneous to the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152178:84"/> VVord of God.</hi> This ought be an inducement to us to preſent and offer the examination of our Confeſſion before the Supreme States, either to ſhew its agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the Word of God, or to render it ſuitable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
               <p>6. Reaſon, is drawn from the example of the Aſſociates of the <hi>Auguſtan Confeſſion;</hi> the <hi>Helveti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>French Churches,</hi> who not above two or three yeeres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, inriched their Confeſſion with a new entire Article; and the Belgick its ſelf, ſince its firſt Edition, hath undergone a Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny in ſubſtraction from it, addition to it, and mutation of it.</p>
               <p>I wave other Reaſons that might be brought, judging theſe ſufficient to prove that the <hi>Clauſe for Examination</hi> and <hi>Review,</hi> as they call it, is rightly inſerted in the <hi>Inſtrument of Conſent,</hi> of which mention was made even now.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:152178:84"/>
               <p>I am not ignorant what Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations are made againſt theſe, eſpecially that publiſhed abroad every where, and judged to carry the greateſt weight (to which I think it requiſite to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer) <hi>That to review the Doctrine of the Church, would be to call the ſame into queſtion,</hi> which neither ought, nor is fit to be done.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it's approved by the ſuffrage of many grave and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, and ſtifly defended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the oppoſers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Seal'd with the blood of ſo many thouſand Martyrs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From hence would ariſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, ſcandals, ruine of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences within the Church, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, reproaches, and criminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons without.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:152178:85"/>
               <p>To all theſe I reply, 1. 'Twere better this odious kinde of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as to call into queſtion, &amp; the like, were not uſed but when only humane Writings are under debate, which may have a mixture of Error in them: What reaſon is there to ſay ſuch a Writing is called into queſtion, <hi>which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver queſtionleſs,</hi> nor ever ought to be ſo reputed?</p>
               <p>2. The defence of any Writing againſt its adverſaries, the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of learned men, the obſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation thereof with the blood of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> ſuffice not to make a Doctrine authentick; theſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Teachers being liable to erre, which is not to be denyed in this Argument.</p>
               <p>3. The Materials of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion</hi> admit of diſcrimination; ſome touch the foundation of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and are the very funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Chriſtianity; ſome on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are built upon this bottm, and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152178:85"/> are not abſolutely in themſelves neceſſary to eternal bliſs. The former are approv'd of by the unanimous conſent of all reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſtrongly defended againſt all gainſayers; the later diſputed to and fro amongſt them, and ſome of theſe not without ſome ſhew of truth oppugned by their Adverſaries. To the firſt of theſe the Martyrs have ſet to their ſeal in blood; to the laſt not at all. It's worthy our diligent obſervation what was propounded to theſe Witneſſes of Religion in our time, and for what their own lives were not dear unto them; which if we do, we ſhall find they were never queſtion'd about any thing judged worthy (by me) of a debate in the Synod; therefore not ſealed with the blood of any. To alledge an example; When the queſtion was concerning the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Cap. to the <hi>Romans,</hi> 'twas aſſerted by ſome, That that place was cited in the Margin of the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152178:86"/> Confeſſion, and that in his ſenſe who avouched the ſame, and that <hi>The Martyrs had ſeal'd the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with their blood.</hi> Anſwer was, If the exacteſt ſearch were made through the great Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs ſet forth by the French, 'twould not be found that ever any of them were ſo much as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd concerning it, or ſhed the leaſt drop of their blood for it: In brief, the blood of thoſe ſacred Witneſſes confirm'd this, <hi>That in the Integrity and ſimplicity of their conſciences they profeſſed the Faith;</hi> and not that their Confeſſion was beyond all Reproof and Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unleſs they had been ſo led into all truth by Chriſt that they could not erre.</p>
               <p>4. If the Church were rightly inſtructed in the <hi>Difference</hi> which is, and ever ought to be 'twixt Divine and Humane Writings, and of that Liberty the Church and all other Chriſtians are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152178:86"/> inveſted with, of regulating the later by the former, they would neither vex themſelves, nor be offended when they ſee all the writings of men brought to the probative touchſtone of Gods Word, but rather 'twould be matter of great joy to the Church, that God had beſtowed ſuch Paſtors and Teachers upon it, who might juſtly and fitly (due order alwayes obſerv'd, to the Teſt. of the Scriptures) level their Doctrine accordingly, that it might every way accord, and in the leaſt things perfectly agree therewith.</p>
               <p>5. The fear of enſuing trouble, the Scorns, Cavillings and Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of diſaffected perſons ought not to render <hi>a Doctrine once received leſs obnoxious to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;</hi> they might rather turn it to their advantage, when 'twould be manifeſt, ſuch perſons as would do this, were not
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152178:87"/> ſound in their Religion, it being of Divine injunction <hi>to ſearch and try the ſpirits whether they were of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If theſe Conſiderations had been of any moment with <hi>Luther, Zwinglius,</hi> and others, the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the <hi>Pontificiar es</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been brought to the teſt by them; neither thoſe who follow the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Confeſſion had jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it reaſonable to ſubject it to a new Examination, and change it in ſome places thereof. We cannot but approve this deed, and judge <hi>Luther</hi> not to have done well, being admoniſhed by <hi>Philip Melancthon</hi> in the cloſe of his life, (as it's teſtified in writing by our Countrey-men) to reduce the Euchariſtical Controverſie of the Lords Supper to ſome better agreement, in refuſing ſo to do upon this ground, retorted upon <hi>Philip,</hi> as 'tis reported of him,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152178:87"/> 
                  <hi>That by this means the whole Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſhould be called into question;</hi> for if reaſons of this nature had been admitted, then the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had been lawful in hindring the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverting and queſtioning by any new ſcrutiny the Doctrine receiv'd in the Church for ſo many hundred yeers.</p>
               <p>To this it's oppoſed, If the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Churches ſhould be ſubjected to a new Examination, at the Celebration of every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Synod, they would never have any thing on which they might reſt and firmly lean; and that it might be truly ſaid of theſe Churches, That they had <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem anniverſariam,</hi> an anual faith, and were carried about <hi>hither and thither with every winde of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> To which I anſwer.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The Church have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, the Evangeliſts
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152178:88"/> and Apoſtles, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) the whole Scripture of the Old &amp; New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament wherein the neceſſaries to ſalvation are fully and clearly comprehended; <hi>Vpon this the Church ſhall build its faith, and ſtay thereon as upon an immovable foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> into which, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Confeſſions &amp; Catechiſms every determination in all cauſes of Faith and Religion ought to be reſolv'd.</p>
               <p>2. There are ſome points in the Confeſſion ſo certain and indubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that they will never be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd by any but <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex. Gr.</hi> Whether Chriſt be the Son of God? Whether the ſoul be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal?</note> Hereticks; other branches are of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that 'twere very advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as oft as may be, to have them debated amongſt learned and God-fearing men, that they may be ranked as neer as poſsibly they can, with points of greater certainty.</p>
               <p>3. It would be endeavoured
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:152178:88"/> that the Confeſsion be made up of as few heads as may be, and thoſe briefly framed in Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terms; omitting all larger Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Proofs, Digreſſions, heapings together of words and ſentences, Amplifications, Excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and onely delivering in it the neceſſaries to ſalvation.</p>
               <p>The brevity will render it leſs obnoxious to Errors, Obloquy, and Examination, taking for our example the practiſe of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, which gave a draught of the Articles judged neceſſary to be believed in very few words.</p>
               <p>Some there are that make a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction betwixt the Confeſsion and Catechiſm, as to a review, and judge the former (becauſe proper to the <hi>Belgick Churches,</hi> and not ſo much made uſe of by others) may with leſs difficulty fall under a Synodical review and examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152178:89"/> but the Catechiſm not being peculiar to us, but chiefly appertaining to the <hi>Palatinate</hi> Churches, and of general uſe and concernment, cannot without great detriment be brought to the teſt. To which I anſwer, If the Catechiſme of <hi>Heydelberg</hi> muſt needs be the form of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord amongſt the Teachers of the Churches, and to which every of them is bound to ſubſcribe, its neceſſary to ſubject the ſame to Examination; for there are no Churches ought to be in that place unto us, that we ſhould ſo admit of any writing compoſed by them, as not to preſerve our Liberty of examining the ſame. And this I look upon as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal cauſe why the Churches of ſeveral Provinces agreeing in the Fundamentals of Religion, have framed their Confeſsions peculiar to every of them. Let it be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the <hi>Heydelberg</hi> Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm is no ſuch <hi>form</hi> and liberty
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152178:89"/> conceded in its Explication as is fitting, and 'twil not be neceſſary either to review or examine the ſame; the burden only of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription thereunto removed, and moderate liberty yeelded in the unfolding thereof.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
            <p>AND this is that (moſt Noble, Potent. Wiſe, and prudent Lords) I have to propoſe to your Highneſſes; together with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of thanks to this Noble and Potent Aſſembly (to which next after God himſelfe, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aedg my ſelfe bound to give an account of all my actions) that of your Clemency you have vouchſafed to heare me patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; with my ſolemne proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that I am ready to entertaine a fraternal and amicable confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with my fellow brethren concerning theſe things, or any other about which at any time
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152178:90"/> any controverſie may ariſe, at what time or place, or upon what occaſion ſoever it ſhall be judged requiſite by theſe Seſſions. And I further engage in every debate to yeeld my ſelf moderate and flexible, not leſs prompt to learn then teach: And in as much as in every thing to be conferr'd of amongſt us, there are two things attendable, Firſt, whether that in debate be true, and then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be neceſſary to be believed unto ſalvation (the Scriptures being the ground of our inquiry in both) I do Sacredly affirm and ſolemnly oblige my ſelfe not to obtrude any point to be believed, my brethren diſſenting from me therein, though proved by ſolid arguments to conſent with the Scriptures, unleſſe I have clearly Evinced it from the Divine word it ſelfe, and as dilucidly true ſo alſo neceſsary to be believed by every Chriſtian to ſalvation; which if my brethren will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152178:90"/> to do, my opinion is, there will ſcarce any debate or Schiſme be amongſt us. And further I adde; (that I may take away all feare and jealouſy that on my part may hang upon this Noble Aſſembly, now charged and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd with weighty affaires, upon which the peace and proſperity of our Nation and the reform'd Churches depend) there will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be very many things, and thoſe of a high nature which I ſhall beare with in my fellow brethren, not being Lord of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans faith, but a Miniſter in this to thoſe that believe, that in them may grow the Knowledg, truth, piety, peace, and joy in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> But if my fellow-brethren ſee not how they can attolerate me and grant me a place amongſt them, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding for that which concern's my ſelf, I hope no rent or diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will enſue, which God avert; there are Schiſms enough already
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152178:91"/> in the Chriſtian world; its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent rather upon every one to diminiſh and aboliſh them. In this caſe, I'le poſſeſs my ſoule in patience: and my place (though I ſhall indeavour to live ſo long as God ſhall prorogue my life for the common good of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) I will lay downe; mindfull of that</p>
            <closer>Sat Eccleſiae, Sat Patriae datum.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:91"/>
            <head>Theſe books following are to be ſold by Henry Everſden, at the Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound in Pauls Church-yard.</head>
            <p>AN Expoſition with Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Obſervations on the Nine firſt Chapters of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, by <hi>Francis Taylor</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in quarto.</p>
            <p>An Expoſition, with Practicall Obſervations on the whole Book of <hi>Canticles</hi> in quarto, by <hi>John Robotham</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Idea,</hi> or body of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcipline in the Theorick and Practick, by Mr. <hi>Rogers,</hi> in quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imputatio Fidei,</hi> Or a Treatiſe of Juſtification; wherein the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Faith for Righteouſneſs (mentioned in <hi>Romans 4. 5. 6th.</hi>) is <hi>explained,</hi> by Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, in quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</p>
            <p>The <hi>Right of Dominions,</hi> or the <hi>Prerogative of Kings,</hi> proved
<pb facs="tcp:152178:92"/> from Scripture, by Dr. <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucas Redivivus,</hi> or the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Phyſitian, preſcribing (by way of meditation) divine Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to prevent diſeaſes, not yet entred upon the ſoul, by <hi>John Anthony</hi> Doctor in Phyſick, in quarto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercy in her Exaltation,</hi> a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached at the Funerall of Mr. <hi>Thomas Taylor,</hi> by Mr. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> in quarto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anabaptiſts Meribah,</hi> or <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſtrife,</hi> being an anſwer to Mr: <hi>Tho. Lamb,</hi> Merchant; by Mr. <hi>Price</hi> one of Mr. <hi>John Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins</hi> Congregation.</p>
            <p>The natural mans caſe ſtated, or an exact map of the little world, man, in ſeventeen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, by Mr. <hi>Christopher Love;</hi> to which is added a Sermon preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at his Funeral, by Mr. <hi>Thomas Manton</hi> of <hi>Newington in</hi> 80.</p>
            <p>Gods glory in mans happineſs, or the freeneſs of Gods grace
<pb facs="tcp:152178:92"/> electing us, by <hi>Francis Taylor</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in 80.</p>
            <p>The Lords Prayer unclaſped, being a vindication of it, againſt all ſchiſmaticks and Hereticks, called <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> and <hi>Fratracilli,</hi> by <hi>James Harwood,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolitus</hi> Tranſlated out of <hi>Seneca,</hi> by <hi>Edm. Preſtwich. Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel publick worſhip,</hi> or the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Metaphraſe, Analyſis, and Expoſition of <hi>Romans</hi> 12. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, to <hi>8th.</hi> deſcribing and preſcribing the compleat pattern of <hi>Goſpel worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo an Expoſition of the <hi>18th</hi> Chapter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>Matthew;</hi> to which is added a diſcovery of <hi>Adams</hi> three-fold eſtate in Paradiſe, viz. <hi>Moral, Legal,</hi> and <hi>Evangelical,</hi> by <hi>Thomas Brewer,</hi> in 80.</p>
            <p>A Comment on <hi>Ruth</hi> together with two Sermons, one teaching how to live wel, the other mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to dye wel; by <hi>Thomas Fuller</hi> Author of the <hi>Holy State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pearls of Eloquence, or the
<pb facs="tcp:152178:93"/> ſchool of Complements, wherein Ladies, and Gentlewomen may accomodate their Courtly prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, by <hi>Will. Elder</hi> Gent. in 12.</p>
            <p>The doctrine of laying on of hands vindicated and aſſerted, being an Anſwer to Lieut. Col. <hi>Paul Hobſon,</hi> in quarto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Male of the <hi>Flock,</hi> a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached before the Lord Mayor, out of the <hi>4th</hi> of <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Aggas</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Chynis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Theſe Books are now in the Preſs and ready to Publiſh.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Riverus</hi> Vniverſall body of Phyſick, in Engliſh folio.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh day Sabbath ſought out and Celebrated by <hi>The. Tillam,</hi> in 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Kendall.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Reſbury,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pauſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:93"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:94"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152178:94"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
